<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The reflecter's defence of his Letter to a friend against the furious assaults of Mr. I.S. in his Second Catholic letter in four dialogues.</title>
            <author>Ellis, Clement, 1630-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39267</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E570</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17613</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12656600</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12656600</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65387</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39267)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65387)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 352:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The reflecter's defence of his Letter to a friend against the furious assaults of Mr. I.S. in his Second Catholic letter in four dialogues.</title>
                  <author>Ellis, Clement, 1630-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Rogers ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reply to John Sergeant's Second Catholick letter.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Ellis Clement. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd. ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sergeant, John, 1622-1707. --  Second Catholick letter.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:65387:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur Liber cui Titulus; <hi>The Reflecter's Defence of his Letter to a Friend,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>Jan.</hi> 18. 1687.</date>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Guil. Needham,</hi> R. R. in Chriſto P. ac D.D. <hi>Wilhelmo</hi> Archiepiſc. <hi>Cant.</hi> à Sacr. Domeſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <p>Note, <hi>(L.) Signifies The Firſt Letter. (A.) The Letter to a Friend or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. (R.) The Reply or Second Catholick Letter.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65387:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Reflecter's Defence</hi> OF HIS LETTER to a FRIEND, AGAINST <hi>The Furious Aſſaults of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               </hi> I. S. In his Second Catholic Letter.</p>
            <p>IN Four <hi>DIALOG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>William Rogers,</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> over againſt St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> MDCLXXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:65387:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65387:2"/>
            <head>A DIALOGUE BETWEEN <hi>I. S.</hi> a Roman-Catholick, AND <hi>C.</hi> a Catholick CHRISTIAN.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>WHatever Honour it may be to <hi>me,</hi> it was, I am ſure, a very wonderful Condeſcenſion in <hi>you,</hi> Sir, to ſtoop ſo low, with all your Glory of <hi>Self-Evidence, Abſolute Certainly</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility,</hi> as to addreſs a <hi>Catholick Better</hi> to one, unto whom you allow no more at beſt, than <hi>honest Ignorance,</hi> and hardly ſo much, when you are a little our of humor, as <hi>common Sence,</hi> or to underſtand <hi>Engliſh.</hi> How civilly, you have therein <hi>Treated</hi> me, how juſtly you have <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed,</hi> or how fully <hi>Confuted</hi> me, is not a thing that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the notice of many. The things we talk of, are too weighty to rely on either mine or your <hi>Wit, Breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Reputation,</hi> or <hi>Skill:</hi> I am not therefore careful either to <hi>Vindicate</hi> or <hi>Recriminate,</hi> or yet to learn of your <hi>Right Catholick Letter,</hi> how to anſwer it as it deſerves. I ſhall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65387:3"/>only, with your good leave, lay the matter open in a plain <hi>Dialogue,</hi> and leave it to every <hi>moderate Judgment</hi> (in your own words) <hi>to ſee by the very Methods we take, which ſide deſires and ſincerely endeavours that</hi> Truth <hi>may appear.</hi> There is only one little <hi>Miſtake</hi> of yours running almoſt quite through your obliging <hi>Letter,</hi> which it concerns me here to give notice of, becauſe it reflects on the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of a <hi>Perſon,</hi> whoſe Books I confeſs my ſelf unworthy to carry after him. Know then, Sir, beſeech you, that you honour me too much in calling me Dr. <hi>St.</hi>'s <hi>Defender,</hi> and my <hi>Letter</hi> a <hi>Defence</hi> of his. I never had the happineſs either by Face to be known by him, or in Word or Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to converſe with him, Neither had I his Letter by me, or knew much more of it, when I writ mine, than what I read in <hi>yours,</hi> which I thought not my ſelf obliged to account all <hi>Oracle.</hi> The <hi>Reputation</hi> therefore of that <hi>Great Man</hi> is no way concerned in my Failings (as you would fain have it); but whatever they are, I alone am to anſwer for them. This I now tell you, becauſe of your (I will not ſay after you, <hi>affected</hi>) <hi>Inadvertence,</hi> who might have ſeen in the Title-page of my <hi>Letter,</hi> that I intended only to <hi>Reflect</hi> on <hi>ſome Paſſages</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you <hi>first;</hi> and alſo in the beginning of it, what they were; all regard to the <hi>Conference</hi> it ſelf, being laid aſide. And this I take to be <hi>Anſwer</hi> enough to a great part of your <hi>Catholick Epiſtle.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Your <hi>Anſwer</hi> affords no work for a <hi>Replier,</hi> but the moſt ungrateful one in the world, to be perpetually telling men of their <hi>Faults,</hi> without the leaſt hopes of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them good, or contributing to their <hi>amendment. R. Pref.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Whether then your <hi>Charity</hi> in judging us incorri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, or your <hi>Wiſdom</hi> in writing ſo long a Letter to no purpoſe, or your <hi>Delight</hi> in troubling the World with Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinences, be the greateſt, I will not now inquire; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65387:3"/>by a ſincere promiſe of Amendment, endeavour to put you in better hopes and a more charitable opinion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Be pleaſed to leave off your <hi>affected Inſincerities,</hi> otherwiſe I muſt be forced to expoſe them yet farther. <hi>R. pag.</hi> 80.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Be pleaſed firſt to exerciſe more your <hi>Charity</hi> in diſcovering them to my ſelf, or I ſhall a little ſuſpect your <hi>Juſtice</hi> in expoſing them to others.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Your conſtant uſe is, to pick out a few words ſcattered here and there, which you thought you might moſt commodiouſly pervert. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>If I pick'd up nothing but what you had ſcatter'd, and anſwer'd all I pick'd up, I did all that I undertook to do. You muſt not perſwade me, that I may not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer ſome periods of a Diſcourſe, without binding my ſelf thereby to anſwer the whole; though you would make the World believe that all my anſwering is only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I have now traced you punctually ſtep by ſtep; wherefore I have reaſon to expect the ſame <hi>exact meaſure</hi> from you. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>How reaſonable a task this is, I will not diſpute; though I know not why your being at more pains than needed, (as you certainly were, if the Anſwer afforded no more work for a Replier) muſt bind me to be ſo too. But ſeeing you have made this my task, I'll endeavour to obey you; only excuſe me, when you ſtep into the Dirt, if I follow you not, leſt I come to need more <hi>Holy-water</hi> than (by your Letter I gueſs) you can well ſpare. However, the way is tedious, and, as you have made it, rugged e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; 'tis time to ſet forth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Perhaps it has ſcarce been ſeen hitherto, that all our <hi>Polemical Conteſts</hi> were reduced within ſo <hi>narrow</hi> a compaſs. <hi>R. Pref.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I like not <hi>[Perhaps,]</hi> I had rather you had ſaid, <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely,</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:65387:4"/>or <hi>Certainly:</hi> Then ſhould I have hoped, ſeeing they narrow ſo faſt, they would ſoon have come to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things. Some of you told us many years ago, when the chief <hi>Queſtion</hi> was, <hi>Which is the only true Church?</hi> That this was the <hi>ſhorteſt Compendium of our Controverſies.</hi> If you have now found a <hi>ſhorter</hi> than the <hi>ſhorteſt,</hi> why ſtand we thus at a diſtance? Let's throw away our Weapons and embrace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>My firſt Letter inſiſted chiefly on two ſhort <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes,</hi> whereof the one undertook to ſhew the <hi>Nullity of the Rule of Faith</hi> claim'd by Dr. <hi>St.</hi> and his <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> the other, the <hi>Abſolute Certainty</hi> of the <hi>Catholic Rule. R. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I hope it will be thought but an <hi>honest Ignorance,</hi> if I be not able to diſtinguiſh Dr. <hi>St.</hi>'s <hi>Proteſtants</hi> from the <hi>Catholick Chriſtians</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> whoſe <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> is the <hi>Holy Scripture.</hi> Remember now what your <hi>two Diſcourſes</hi> undertook to ſhew; and when that is ſhown indeed, (and I wiſh you be not in too good earneſt to ſhew it) <hi>wonderful things</hi> (as you ſpeak) will follow, and you will be ſure of many <hi>Converts;</hi> yea, I dare ſay, even of Dr. <hi>St.</hi> and all his <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> In the mean time, what a neat way of <hi>reducing Controverſies</hi> to a <hi>narrower compaſs</hi> is this, whereby the <hi>Diſputants</hi> have not left them any <hi>common Rule,</hi> whereby it may be determined who is in the right?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>whole Controverſie</hi> was, in ſhort, about the <hi>Certainty</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainty</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian Faith. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe words would make one think you are <hi>Narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> our Conteſts into a <hi>wider</hi> compaſs yet; as if the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute</hi> had been betwixt <hi>Believers</hi> and <hi>Infidels:</hi> and then which Party you would have the <hi>Infidel,</hi> denying the <hi>Certainty</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> would not be hard to find. It's a little oddly expreſſed, but I am willing to make the beſt on't, and to think that you mean no more than what
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65387:4"/>you ſaid but now, that it was about the <hi>Nullity</hi> of <hi>our Rule,</hi> and the <hi>Abſolute Certainty</hi> of <hi>yours.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Both of thoſe <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> were ſuppoſed by us to be <hi>Concluſive. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I doubt it not, but you thought them <hi>Abſolute Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations;</hi> yet I was bold to tell my <hi>Friend</hi> in a <hi>Letter,</hi> I thought you were miſtaken.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Your whole <hi>Letter</hi> ſeems to have no other deſign, but to bring the <hi>Diſpute</hi> into a <hi>Wrangle. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>And you, I thank you, took care it ſhould not loſe its deſign, if that was it; and have return'd me nothing elſe but a <hi>Wrongle</hi> for a <hi>Reply.</hi> But let's fall to our Buſineſs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I grieve and wonder there ſhould be ſo little <hi>value</hi> for <hi>Souls</hi> among your <hi>Party,</hi> as to ſend men to the <hi>Tribunal</hi> of God, without furniſhing them with <hi>Aſſurance</hi> that they can <hi>juſtifie</hi> their <hi>Accounts</hi> themſelves. <hi>R. p.</hi> 2.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Speak you this in good earneſt, as conſidering how <hi>you</hi> ſhall juſtifie <hi>your Accounts</hi> your ſelf at that <hi>Tribunal?</hi> What bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter courſe our Party takes to furniſh men with ſuch <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> than yours doth, I told you, <hi>A. p.</hi> 3. whereof you are not pleaſed to take any notice, though you were ſo punctual in tracing me ſtep by ſtep. Now I muſt needs continue my wonder, ſeeing no man can be <hi>aſſured</hi> that he can juſtifie his <hi>Accounts,</hi> unleſs he know that he hath the <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and ſeeing you, being a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> believe the <hi>Council of Trent,</hi> ſaying, <hi>No man can know that he hath obtain'd the Grace of God,</hi> how you can be ſo unreaſonably exacting, as to require that of our <hi>Party,</hi> which your ſelf believe no man can do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>If you ſpeak, as I did, of an <hi>Account</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> I hope you will not perſwade us, a man cannot know <hi>why he believes,</hi> without knowing whether he be in a <hi>ſtate of Grace. R. p.</hi> 3.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>And I hope you will not endeavour to perſwade us, that a mans bare knowing <hi>why he believes,</hi> will enable him to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his <hi>Account,</hi> even of his <hi>Faith</hi> it ſelf. We know <hi>why we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> the <hi>Chriſtian Faith;</hi> think you we are therefore able to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65387:5"/>juſtifie our <hi>Account</hi> of <hi>Faith?</hi> Then our <hi>Diſpute</hi> is ended. Suppoſe another may know why <hi>he believes</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> to be <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt,</hi> (as I am ſure he may, whether it be <hi>true</hi> or <hi>falſe,</hi> and his Reaſons <hi>good</hi> or <hi>bad</hi>) I hope you will not grant he can thereby juſtifie his <hi>Account</hi> of <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The bare <hi>Aſſurance</hi> of the <hi>Truth</hi> which a man believes is a <hi>Juſtification</hi> of his <hi>believing</hi> it. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>You ſpake of an <hi>Account that will paſs, as it is in it ſelf,</hi> (<hi>L. p.</hi> 5.) but this <hi>Account</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> will not paſs, as it is in it ſelf without <hi>Grace.</hi> Such a bare <hi>Aſſurance</hi> will only be ſuch a <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification</hi> of a man's <hi>believing,</hi> as will add to his <hi>condemnation,</hi> for <hi>holding the Truth in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>knowing his Maſter's will without doing it.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>If you ſpeak of an <hi>Account</hi> of our <hi>whole lives,</hi>—you turn things againſt the plain <hi>ſcope</hi> of my <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> againſt my plain <hi>words,</hi> and (I much fear) againſt your own <hi>knowledge. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Your <hi>ſcope</hi> in this part of your <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> was evidently this, to make our <hi>Party</hi> appear <hi>careleſs</hi> of mens <hi>Souls.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The only <hi>Queſtion</hi> was of the <hi>Certainty</hi> of <hi>Proteſtant Faith;</hi>—An <hi>Account</hi> why you <hi>Proteſtants</hi> believe—was the only <hi>Account</hi> that belongs to that <hi>Queſtion. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>That <hi>Queſtion,</hi> and the ſhifting off the <hi>Proof</hi> to another, you wave in the beginning of your <hi>third Section</hi> (<hi>L. p.</hi> 4.) ſaying. <hi>Of this Propoſal there will be occaſion to ſay more by and by. At preſent conſider</hi> (ſay you) <hi>how you deal with Souls who rely on you:</hi> And all through the <hi>Section</hi> your buſineſs is to charge us with <hi>careleſneſs</hi> of mens <hi>Souls.</hi> I ſuppoſe you mean, eſpecially in our not giving them <hi>Aſſurance</hi> of their <hi>Faith.</hi> This being the <hi>Fault</hi> you charge our <hi>Party</hi> with, you thus proceed to aggravate it: <hi>Muſt not every body one day bring in his own Account?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And will not the happineſs or miſery of their Souls depend on that Account? Can you ſuffer them to run that terrible hazard, without making them able to</hi> juſtifie <hi>their</hi> Accounts <hi>themſelves, and furniſhing them with</hi> Aſſurance <hi>that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65387:5"/>they can?</hi> &amp;c. Theſe are your plain <hi>words;</hi> and if I miſtook them, it was no <hi>wilful miſtake,</hi> but occaſioned merely hence, that I thought you had diſcourſed with more ſhew of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> than indeed you did. For no better <hi>Reaſon</hi> could be given, why we muſt <hi>fail</hi> in <hi>Duty,</hi> if we furniſh not men with <hi>Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> that they can <hi>account</hi> for their <hi>Faith,</hi> than this, becauſe it is our Duty to furniſh them with <hi>Aſſurance</hi> that they can juſtifie their <hi>Accounts</hi> (as you ſet it) in the <hi>plural,</hi> of which the <hi>Account</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> is one. However, becauſe I ſaw you are one that love to walk in the <hi>dark,</hi> ſo that he who <hi>traces</hi> you moſt diligently, may poſſibly <hi>miſs</hi> you; and when you are <hi>hit,</hi> have a trick of crying out, <hi>You miſtake, it is not I.</hi> I aim'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and <hi>hit</hi> right. My Fault then, if it was one, was no ſooner ſpied than amended; and if it may be forgiven, I am content that <hi>you</hi> and your <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent</hi> ſhall be good friends as long as you can agree on't.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I had alledged further, that till <hi>Proteſtants</hi> produce the <hi>Grounds</hi> which prove their <hi>Faith</hi> to be <hi>true,</hi> it cannot with <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> be held <hi>Truth.</hi> You put my Diſcourſe firſt in my words, only <hi>leaving out</hi> thoſe which did not pleaſe you. <hi>R. p.</hi> 4.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Your <hi>words</hi> are theſe: <hi>Truth is therefore Truth, becauſe 'tis built on intrinfical grounds which prove it to be ſuch; and not on private mens abilities, or their ſaying this or that: wherefore till thoſe grounds be produced, it cannot be with Reaſon held Truth.</hi> I left out indeed the words <hi>[therefore]</hi> and <hi>[which prove it to be ſuch]</hi> not becauſe I <hi>diſliked</hi> them, but becauſe I thought them <hi>ſuperfluous,</hi> as being <hi>implied</hi> in the reſt. Well, now you have them, what will they <hi>avail you,</hi> or <hi>hurt me?</hi> All I deſire of you is, that you will ſtick as cloſe to your <hi>own words,</hi> as you would tye me to do; which I ſuſpect you will hardly do, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you begin to vary more than I did already, eſpecially in leaving out the word <hi>[intrinfical.]</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Then you <hi>diſguiſe</hi> it in your <hi>own,</hi> and <hi>laugh</hi> at it for being too <hi>plain. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe are my <hi>words: You might as well have ſaid more
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65387:6"/>plainly, What any thing is, that it is, whatever be the reaſon why it is ſo, or whoſoever ſaith it is or it is not; yet can no man with reaſon believe it, till he have a reaſon to believe it.</hi> This I ſtill take to be <hi>all</hi> that you meant by <hi>Truth's being built on intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Grounds,</hi> &amp;c. And you ſeem to <hi>confeſs</hi> it by your ſaying nothing to the contrary; for you are not <hi>he</hi> that uſeth not to tell all the World when he is wrong'd. I gather hence, that in your Account, To ſay a thing more <hi>plainly,</hi> is to <hi>diſguiſe</hi> it; and to ſay we <hi>know</hi> it, is to <hi>laugh</hi> at it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Thence you <hi>ſtart aſide</hi> to tell us, <hi>That the</hi> Vulgar Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick <hi>has leſs</hi> Certainty <hi>than the</hi> Vulgar Proteſtant, <hi>becauſe the one has only the Word of his</hi> Prieſt, <hi>the other hath the Word of his</hi> Miniſter, <hi>and the Word of</hi> God <hi>in</hi> Seripture <hi>beſides. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Had I a mind to turn the <hi>Diſpute</hi> into a <hi>Wrangle,</hi> I ſhould here tell you, as you did me, You <hi>leave out</hi> thoſe words you do not like. But <hi>take</hi> and <hi>leave</hi> what you pleaſe. Only tell me why I muſt be thought to <hi>ſtare aſide,</hi> when I ſtep <hi>ſtraight for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> only to a <hi>concluſion,</hi> which naturally follows from your own <hi>Premiſes?</hi> If <hi>Truth</hi> depend on <hi>intrinſical grounds,</hi> and not on mens ſaying <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that;</hi> can it depend any more on the Word of your <hi>Prieſt,</hi> than of our <hi>Miniſter?</hi> And therefore if the Word of your <hi>Prieſts</hi> be all that your <hi>Vulgar Catholics</hi> have, doth it not alſo follow on this ſuppoſition, that they have leſs <hi>certainty</hi> than <hi>Vulgar Proteſtants</hi> have, who have, beſides the Words of their <hi>Miniſters,</hi> the Word of God too. But this is to walk where you have no mind to ſee me, and therefore it muſt needs be a <hi>ſtarting aſide</hi> out of the way.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Do <hi>you</hi> think <hi>Catholick Prieſts</hi> are at liberty to tell the <hi>Vulgar</hi> what <hi>Faith</hi> they pleaſe, as your <hi>Miniſters</hi> may <hi>interpret Scripture</hi> as ſeems beſt to their <hi>judgment of Diſeretion!</hi> When you cannot but know they <hi>dare</hi> not teach them any <hi>Faith,</hi> but what the <hi>Church</hi> holds; nor does the <hi>Church</hi> hold any, but upon <hi>Tradition. R. p.</hi> 4.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Say</hi> and <hi>Prove,</hi> Sir, is your own Rule, and thereby you have here ſet your ſelf a very hard task. <hi>Prove</hi> then <hi>We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65387:6"/>but know</hi> firſt, <hi>That your</hi> Church <hi>holds no</hi> Faith <hi>but upon</hi> Tradition, whilſt the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent</hi> takes the <hi>Word written,</hi> as well as <hi>unwritten Traditions,</hi> for the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Verity</hi> and <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline. Prove</hi> again, that the ſame <hi>Council</hi> held no <hi>Faith</hi> but upon <hi>Tradition,</hi> decreeing the <hi>No-neceſſity of Communicating in both kinds,</hi> and yet confeſſing there was neither <hi>Scripture</hi> nor <hi>Tradition</hi> to build that bold <hi>Decree</hi> upon. <hi>Prove, We know that your Prieſts dare teach no Faith but what the Church holds.</hi> Not to mention any more, Have none of them ever taught the <hi>Pope's Depoſing Power?</hi> And doth your <hi>Church</hi> give that <hi>liberty,</hi> or <hi>dare</hi> they do it without her leave? Yet be it all as you ſay, Have the <hi>Vulgar Catholicks</hi> any more than the <hi>Prieſt's</hi> word for their <hi>Faith?</hi> If not, what I ſaid is true, and they cannot with <hi>reaſon</hi> hold your <hi>Doctrine</hi> for <hi>Truth,</hi> unleſs you will have a <hi>groundleſs preſumption</hi> that <hi>Prieſts dare not teach any Faith but what the Church holds,</hi> paſs for an <hi>intrinfical ground of Truth, which proves</hi> all they teach <hi>to be ſuch.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Again, you do well to ſay your People have it in <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> or in a <hi>Book,</hi> for they have it no-where elſe. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>If by <hi>[it]</hi> you mean the <hi>Word of God,</hi> I ſay they have it there.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You know <hi>Vulgar Socinians</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and all the <hi>rest,</hi> have it as much there. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>For what reaſon you couple <hi>Socinians</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians</hi> ſo frequently, I muſt not now ſtay to ask. I grant they have the <hi>Word of God</hi> in the <hi>Scripture</hi> as well as we.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Then I ſuppoſe you do not think they truly have the <hi>Word of God</hi> on their ſide. <hi>R. p.</hi> 5.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I do not think that any, who <hi>err in Faith</hi> have the <hi>Word of God</hi> on <hi>their ſide.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>To tell me, that <hi>Truth</hi> can depend no more upon the ſaying of a <hi>Romiſh Priest,</hi> than of an <hi>Engliſh Miniſter,</hi> when I tell you it depends not on any <hi>private man's</hi> ſaying, is not the Reply of a man <hi>well awake. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Let it paſs but for a <hi>Dream,</hi> if you pleaſe. Yet may the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65387:7"/>
                  <hi>Interpretation</hi> of it be of ſome concernment to your <hi>Vulgar Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks.</hi> For if I ſay <hi>true,</hi> as you grant I do, then whilſt they have no more but the Word of their <hi>Prieſts</hi> to build their <hi>Faith</hi> upon, they have (according to <hi>me</hi>) <hi>leſs Certainty</hi> than the <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Proteſtants,</hi> and (according to <hi>you) none</hi> at all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>But <hi>two</hi> things more, ſay you, follow from my <hi>Poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> which you fear I will not grant. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I remember them very well. The <hi>First</hi> was, <hi>That we cannot with</hi> Reaſon <hi>hold any thing for a Truth,</hi> merely <hi>becauſe the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> Rome <hi>hath</hi> determined <hi>it; for her</hi> Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>is no</hi> intrinſical <hi>ground of</hi> Truth, <hi>but only an</hi> outward Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony <hi>or</hi> Declaration <hi>of it: and then what's become either of her</hi> Infallibility, <hi>or</hi> Authority <hi>to command our</hi> Faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Slips of <hi>honest Ignorance</hi> deſerve <hi>Compaſſion</hi> and <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;</hi> and becauſe I do not know this to be any more, I will be ſo charitable as to ſet you right. <hi>R. p.</hi> 5.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Such <hi>Slips</hi> I may be guilty of, for I am but a <hi>Man,</hi> and am not exempt from <hi>humane Infirmities:</hi> I ſhall thankfully therefore accept your <hi>Compaſſion,</hi> be attentive to your <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> and the rarer ſuch <hi>Charity</hi> appears in <hi>you,</hi> the more highly do I prize it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Authority,</hi> amongſt thoſe who already admit it for <hi>true,</hi> has force to <hi>prove</hi> that to be <hi>Truth</hi> which depends upon it, and will conclude againſt thoſe who allow its <hi>Veracity,</hi> if it be ſhewn to be engaged <hi>against</hi> them. <hi>R. p.</hi> 5, 6.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>By the way, what kind of <hi>Authority</hi> do you ſpeak of?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Humane Authority,</hi> ſuch as that of the <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility</hi> whereof, in deriving down <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> we go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, you ſee, to demonſtrate. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>So far good; but now, ſuppoſing this <hi>Authority</hi> be of force with thoſe who <hi>already admit</hi> it, what is it, I pray tell me, which can <hi>oblige</hi> men to admit it? If nothing, they may reject it, and be blameleſs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>It has not this <hi>effect</hi> upon humane nature by its <hi>proper power,</hi> as 'tis <hi>meer Authority;</hi> but becauſe <hi>intrinſical Mediums</hi> juſtifie it <hi>worthy</hi> to be relied on. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:65387:7"/>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Muſt not thoſe <hi>intrinſical Mediums</hi> be <hi>known,</hi> before it can <hi>oblige</hi> men to <hi>admit</hi> it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Let that <hi>Authority</hi> come into <hi>diſpute,</hi> it will loſe its <hi>credit,</hi> unleſs it can be prov'd by ſuch <hi>Mediums</hi> to <hi>deſerve</hi> what it pretends to. <hi>No Authority deſerves any Aſſent further than Reaſon gives it to deſerve. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Till that <hi>Reaſon</hi> then appear, no man is bound to <hi>aſſent</hi> unto it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Authority</hi> of the whole <hi>Catholick Church</hi> would be no greater than that of an <hi>Old Woman,</hi> were there no more <hi>reaſon</hi> to be given for believing the <hi>former,</hi> than there is for believing the <hi>later. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I hear all this; have you any more to add for my <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction?</hi> I would not loſe a drop of your <hi>Compaſſion,</hi> it is ſo rare a thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>By this time I hope you ſee, that <hi>all Truths are built upon intrinſical Mediums. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Not one jot more, I aſſure you, than I did before: for you have neither told me what you mean by <hi>intrinſical Mediums,</hi> only you ſeem to hint that they are <hi>Reaſons</hi> why a thing is to be believed, and ſo are <hi>extrinſical Mediums</hi> to; neither have you ſaid a word that I know of, to ſhew how <hi>all Truth is built upon them.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You ſee alſo, that whereas you apprehended they would overthrow our <hi>Church's Teſtimony</hi> or <hi>Authority,</hi> ſuch <hi>Mediums</hi> (in caſe we <hi>produce</hi> them) are the beſt means to eſtabliſh it, and give it <hi>force</hi> upon our ſelves and others. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>This alſo I ſee juſt as much as I did before. You ſuppoſe I <hi>apprehended</hi> (why, you know beſt, for I am half confident you never apprehended I did ſo) that the <hi>intrinfical Reaſons</hi> of your <hi>Church's Authority,</hi> when produced, would overthrow it. To whoſe <hi>roving Fancy</hi> owe we this <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>fine Invention.</hi> Sir? That which I <hi>apprehended,</hi> was this, That ſeeing <hi>all Truths</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on <hi>intrinfical grounds,</hi> as you ſay, and cannot be <hi>held Truths,</hi> till thoſe <hi>intrinſical grounds</hi> of them be <hi>produced:</hi> Therefore they are not to be <hi>held Truths</hi> for the <hi>Authority</hi> of your
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65387:8"/>
                  <hi>Church,</hi> becauſe that <hi>Authority</hi> (whatever it be, and on what <hi>intrinſical grounds</hi> ſoever eſtabliſh'd) is no <hi>intrinſical ground</hi> of thoſe <hi>Truths</hi> to be believed. And have you yet ſaid one word to contradict this? Not a ſyllable, but talk at random of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You alſo ſee, how it comes, that the <hi>Church</hi> can oblige to <hi>belief,</hi> not by a <hi>dry commanding</hi> our <hi>Faith,</hi> as you apprehend; but by having its <hi>humane Authority</hi> ſolidly grounded upon <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> it ſelf becomes a <hi>Motive</hi> able to beget <hi>aſſent. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Now, Sir, I thank you, you have ſet me <hi>right,</hi> juſt <hi>as I was before.</hi> What I ſaw, you have made me ſee; and what I ſaw not, I ſee not yet. Such is the illuminating vertue of your <hi>compaſſionate Inſtructions.</hi> I ask not you, whether this great pains to tell me what I knew, and had told you ſo, was the buſineſs of a man <hi>well awake.</hi> Yet leſt you ſhould ſay, I was not <hi>attentive,</hi> I will repeat to you the <hi>Leſſon</hi> you have taught me. Your <hi>Church's Authority</hi> is <hi>Humane Authority,</hi> it has <hi>force</hi> to <hi>prove</hi> the <hi>Truths</hi> which <hi>depend</hi> upon it; it has this <hi>force</hi> amongſt thoſe that <hi>admit</hi> it, and it concludes <hi>against</hi> ſuch as <hi>own</hi> its <hi>Veracity;</hi> it deſerves no <hi>Aſſent</hi> farther than <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> gives it to <hi>deſerve,</hi> nor is it greater than that of an <hi>Old Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> till better <hi>Reaſon</hi> be produced for it. Hence I conclude, Seeing we <hi>admit</hi> not your <hi>Church's Authority,</hi> neither <hi>own</hi> its <hi>Veracity,</hi> it <hi>proves</hi> nothing to us, nor <hi>concludes</hi> any thing <hi>againſt</hi> us. Seeing <hi>Articles of Faith depend</hi> not on <hi>Humane Authority,</hi> your <hi>Church's Authority</hi> can have no <hi>effect</hi> on humane Nature to <hi>oblige</hi> to a <hi>belief</hi> of them. Seeing all its <hi>Credit</hi> depends on its <hi>intrinſical Reaſons produced,</hi> till they be produced, we are not bound to give any <hi>credit</hi> to it. When theſe <hi>Reaſons</hi> ſhall be <hi>produced,</hi> its <hi>Teſtimony</hi> has but the nature of an <hi>external Motive,</hi> not of an <hi>intrinſical Ground.</hi> And therefore either your <hi>Poſition</hi> overthrows your <hi>Church's Authority,</hi> or <hi>it</hi> your <hi>Poſition,</hi> chuſe you which.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>What is the <hi>Second</hi> thing you fear I will not grant?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>If your <hi>Poſition</hi> be true, it will follow, <hi>That the common
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65387:8"/>People muſt be allow'd their</hi> Judgment <hi>of</hi> Diſcretion: <hi>for how, without the free uſe of that, they ſhall diſcern the</hi> intrinſical grounds <hi>of</hi> Truth <hi>when produced, and ſo with</hi> Reaſon <hi>hold it, I fear you cannot eaſily demonſtrate.</hi> Will you grant us this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You gave your ſelf the <hi>Character</hi> of a <hi>Scrupulous</hi> man; and I ſee by this, you have a mind to maintain it. <hi>R. p.</hi> 7.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>And if you will grant it, you will gain the <hi>Character</hi> of a man much more <hi>liberal</hi> than your <hi>Neighbours.</hi> If you grant it, 'tis I doubt, but in <hi>mockery,</hi> becauſe you ſo often laugh at us for deſiring it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You know that thoſe who <hi>write</hi> and <hi>print,</hi> can have no deſign their <hi>Books</hi> ſhould not be <hi>read;</hi> and you know thoſe that <hi>read,</hi> will and muſt <hi>judge</hi> of what they do <hi>read. R. p.</hi> 7.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yet if their <hi>Books</hi> contain nothing elſe but <hi>unſenſed Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters</hi> (which is the thing you ſay of the <hi>Scripture</hi>) and he that <hi>reads</hi> or <hi>interprets</hi> gives the <hi>ſenſe,</hi> I ſee not to what end they would have their Books <hi>read,</hi> and therefore neither why they <hi>write</hi> them: nor indeed how any one can <hi>judge</hi> of them, unleſs they would have them <hi>judg</hi> only of the <hi>fineneſs</hi> of the <hi>Characters.</hi> Pray, Sir, let me ask you, Can you think <hi>God</hi> writes to leſs pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe than <hi>men</hi> are wont to do? If he have cauſed a <hi>Book</hi> to be <hi>written,</hi> and that to <hi>all,</hi> was it not his <hi>Will</hi> that his <hi>Book</hi> ſhould alſo be <hi>read</hi> of <hi>all</hi> to whom it was <hi>written?</hi> or did he not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend they ſhould <hi>judge</hi> of what they <hi>read</hi> therein, and <hi>exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Doctrines</hi> by it? Do you now grant us this <hi>Judgment</hi> of <hi>Diſcretion</hi> as exerciſed about <hi>Divine Truths</hi> revealed in the <hi>Scripture?</hi> If you do, I thank you for it: If not, to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is your talk of <hi>reading mens Books,</hi> or <hi>their writing</hi> them that we may <hi>judge?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed I think it no great ſign of a <hi>Judgment</hi> of <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion,</hi> to pretend to <hi>diſcern</hi> the <hi>Truth</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> by <hi>Lights</hi> that do not ſhew it to be <hi>true. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Nor I neither.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You conclude, that I have ſet us all on <hi>even ground.</hi> Yes, for I ſet <hi>Abſolute Certainty</hi> on the <hi>one</hi> ſide, and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:65387:9"/>on the <hi>other;</hi> and this, in your Language, is <hi>even ground. R. p.</hi> 8.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>What I conclude, is thus proved: <hi>The</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> Rome <hi>is to be believed only when ſhe produceth the</hi> intrinſical <hi>grounds of</hi> Truth, <hi>and juſt ſo far is the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> England; <hi>or any other</hi> Church <hi>to be believed, and ſo all are of equal</hi> Authority <hi>to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige in points of</hi> Faith. This in my Language is <hi>even ground:</hi> for the <hi>one</hi> ſtands no <hi>higher</hi> in <hi>Authority</hi> than the <hi>other.</hi> Now ſay what you pleaſe of your <hi>Certainty</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainty</hi> to gain the <hi>higher ground</hi> again.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Suppoſe we could not prove that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are <hi>not certain,</hi> are they therefore <hi>certain? L. p.</hi> 4.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>You imagine (it ſhould ſeem) that <hi>all the certainty</hi> of our <hi>Faith</hi> is this, that <hi>Papiſts</hi> cannot prove it to be <hi>uncertain. A. p.</hi> 6.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>meaning</hi> of my words is clearly this, That the <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Faith</hi> muſt depend on their <hi>own proofs</hi> for it, not on any <hi>man</hi>'s being <hi>able</hi> or not <hi>able</hi> to <hi>prove</hi> the contrary. <hi>R. p.</hi> 8.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>You <hi>meant</hi> ſo, you ſay, and the thing is <hi>true.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>To avoid <hi>proving,</hi> you put upon me the direct <hi>contrary</hi> to what I affirm'd, <hi>viz. That the</hi> certainty <hi>of</hi> Proteſtant Faith <hi>does depend upon our not</hi> proving <hi>they have none.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I put no ſuch thing upon you, nor needed I do it to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void <hi>proving;</hi> which I had never undertaken, but only to <hi>reflect</hi> on ſome parts of your <hi>Letter,</hi> who had undertaken to <hi>prove</hi> the <hi>Nullity</hi> of our <hi>Rule.</hi> Allow me then to give my own <hi>meaning,</hi> as you take the liberty to give yours. My <hi>meaning</hi> was this (<hi>clearly</hi> enough to him that would not <hi>wrangle</hi>): You imagine we have <hi>no certainty</hi> at all, and that we think our ſelves well enough, as long as you cannot <hi>prove</hi> we have none.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Well, but did I ſay <hi>true</hi> or no?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>In that which you ſay you <hi>meant,</hi> you ſay <hi>true.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe I ſaid then, our <hi>not proving</hi> the <hi>contrary</hi> is no
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65387:9"/>
                  <hi>certainty</hi> to <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> you will have me imagine it is their <hi>certainty,</hi> nay <hi>all</hi> their <hi>certainty. R. p.</hi> 9.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Not that it is our <hi>certainty,</hi> ſo as we are therefore <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> yet <hi>all</hi> our <hi>certainty,</hi> for you imagine we have <hi>no other.</hi> And now 'tis my turn to ask, Do I ſay <hi>true</hi> or no? If true, why ſay you I wrong you? If no, you <hi>grant</hi> we have ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>certainty,</hi> though you undertook to <hi>ſhew</hi> we have none.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You know well enough, that to prove <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have no <hi>Abſolute certainty</hi> of their <hi>Faith,</hi> is no hard task for a <hi>weak man. L. p.</hi> 6.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I meddle not yet with the word <hi>[Abſolute]:</hi> But ask, how know we this? <hi>A. p.</hi> 6.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You know any man may find it <hi>confeſs'd</hi> to his hand by <hi>Proteſtants. L. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Who, I pray, are thoſe <hi>Proteſtants?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> in his <hi>Rule of Faith,</hi> p. 117, 118. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> is but <hi>one Proteſtant;</hi> yet I am content he ſhould paſs for <hi>many.</hi> But his <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have no <hi>certainty,</hi> I find not. <hi>A.</hi> 6, 7.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>No <hi>Abſolute certainty,</hi> if it pleaſe you. <hi>R. p.</hi> 10.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It pleaſes me not, and I'll tell you why anon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>If you do not underſtand <hi>Engliſh,</hi> I cannot help it; but any one that does, may find it, <hi>p.</hi> 118. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>He ſaith there, that we are not <hi>infallibly certain,</hi> &amp;c. but yet have ſuch an <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> as there is not any <hi>just cauſe</hi> of the <hi>least doubt.</hi> Not a word find I of <hi>Abſolute certainty.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You would perſwade us you ſee it not. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Nor <hi>you</hi> neither, if you may be believed againſt your ſelf; for you tell us, We <hi>ſeem</hi> to <hi>grant</hi> we are thus <hi>abſolutely certain</hi> or <hi>infallible</hi> by virtue of <hi>Tradition, A. p.</hi> 7. If we <hi>ſeem</hi> to you to grant we are <hi>abſolutely certain,</hi> how can you <hi>ſee</hi> our <hi>Confeſſion</hi> that we are not ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>As if it were ſo ſtrange a thing for <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict</hi> one another. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>No very <hi>ſtrange</hi> thing, I confeſs, no not for <hi>Papiſts,</hi> even
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65387:10"/>
                  <hi>Popes</hi> and <hi>Councils.</hi> Though it may ſeem <hi>ſtrange</hi> to ſome, that Pretenders to <hi>Infallibility</hi> ſhould do ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Dr. <hi>St.</hi> did ſay at the <hi>Conference,</hi> They are <hi>abſolutely certain:</hi> And Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> did ſay, we are not <hi>infallibly cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It may be ſo; I ſee not the Contradiction yet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>If one of thoſe Writers do not <hi>ſeem</hi> to grant, that they are <hi>abſolutely certain</hi> (or <hi>infallible</hi>) and the other <hi>confeſs</hi> they have no <hi>abſolute certainty, Engliſh</hi> is no intelligible Language in <hi>England. R. p.</hi> 10, 11.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Well, ſuppoſe we at preſent, for your ſake, that theſe two <hi>Reverend Perſons</hi> did <hi>contradict</hi> each other, will this prove that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have no <hi>certainty</hi> of their <hi>Faith?</hi> Remember that you are ſpeaking of <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> as may make it no hard task for a <hi>weak man</hi> to <hi>prove</hi> that they have no <hi>abſolute certainty</hi> of their <hi>Faith.</hi> Do you think the <hi>Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of <hi>one</hi> ſingle <hi>Proteſtant</hi> enough for this? Allow us but this way of <hi>proof,</hi> and ſee if it be not as eaſie for us (as <hi>weak men</hi> as we are) to <hi>prove</hi> the <hi>uncertainty</hi> of all your new <hi>Trentan Creed,</hi> yea and of <hi>Tradition</hi> too. Again, if the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of <hi>one Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> be <hi>proof</hi> enough for <hi>Proteſtant <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainty,</hi> tell me, with all your <hi>Learning,</hi> why the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of <hi>one Doctor</hi> ſhould not be as good a <hi>proof</hi> for <hi>Proteſtant Certainty?</hi> Your <hi>Weights</hi> and <hi>Scales</hi> you ſo much talk of, would do well here, to ſhew which <hi>Doctor's Authority</hi> weighs moſt, and whether your <hi>proof</hi> weigh any thing at all. You have undertaken to <hi>ſhew the Nullity of the Proteſtant Rule,</hi> and thus you <hi>prove</hi> it, <hi>one</hi> Proteſtant <hi>confeſſed they had no</hi> abſolute certainty, <hi>another ſaid they had; therefore</hi> Proteſtants <hi>have no</hi> certain Rule <hi>of</hi> Faith, <hi>or no</hi> certainty of Faith. 'Tis eaſie indeed for any <hi>weak man</hi> to <hi>prove</hi> at this rate, that is, ſo as becomes a very weak man indeed. Once more I muſt mind you of your <hi>Poſition.</hi> For if all <hi>Truths</hi> be proved by <hi>intrinſical grounds,</hi> and depend not on <hi>private</hi> mens ſaying <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that,</hi> then the <hi>uncertainty</hi> of <hi>Proteſtant Faith</hi> cannot be proved (no not by <hi>I. S.</hi> himſelf)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65387:10"/>from the <hi>ſaying</hi> of either <hi>Doctor,</hi> eſpecially if the one <hi>contradict</hi> what the other ſaith, as you ſuppoſe, but have not yet <hi>proved.</hi> Are <hi>not infallibly certain,</hi> and <hi>abſolutely certain,</hi> contradictory terms?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I proved formerly, that <hi>abſolutely certain,</hi> and <hi>infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> are all one; and it will come into play again are long. <hi>R. p.</hi> 11.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It's well if your proof be not all <hi>Play:</hi> When I ſee it, I'll tell you what I think of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>However, I only ſaid, They <hi>ſeem'd to grant,</hi> &amp;c. For the <hi>Tenet</hi> of <hi>Faiths certainty,</hi> I may ſpeak what I think, is <hi>hearty</hi> in them, its <hi>abſolute certainty</hi> is but <hi>ſeeming. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Speak what you think?</hi> By all means, Sir. How elſe ſhould we know you are made a competent <hi>Judge</hi> of <hi>Hearts,</hi> or your great <hi>charity</hi> in <hi>judging</hi> us <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> ſaying what we think not; or that when you charge men with a <hi>contradiction,</hi> you mean only a <hi>ſeeming contrudiction,</hi> whilſt your ſelf think they mean the ſame thing; or laſtly, the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of the <hi>weak man's proof,</hi> proving that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have <hi>no certainty,</hi> becauſe he thinks the <hi>Tenet</hi> of <hi>Faiths uncertainty</hi> is <hi>hearty</hi> in them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>It is plain, that where <hi>Churches</hi> differ in <hi>Faith, infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Faith</hi> in <hi>one,</hi> cannot ſtand with <hi>certain Faith</hi> in the <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. L. p.</hi> 8.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Whence you may do well to take notice, that when our <hi>Certainty</hi> is once <hi>proved,</hi> no more is needful to <hi>confute</hi> your <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility. A. p.</hi> 8.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abſolute certainty;</hi> I pray you again, for Dr. <hi>St.</hi>'s ſake. <hi>R. p.</hi> 13.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Certainty</hi> is enough, Sir; for that's it in <hi>our Church,</hi> which you ſay <hi>Infallibility</hi> in <hi>yours</hi> cannot ſtand with. And you ſay <hi>true;</hi> though you leave out <hi>Abſolute.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>It bodes ill, that you would have the word <hi>[abſolutely]</hi> left out; it would make a jealous man ſuſpect you had a deſign to palm a <hi>certainty</hi> upon us, which will prove <hi>no certainty. R. p.</hi> 13.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:65387:11"/>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Ill to you, it may be, in that you cannot ſo confidently hereafter call on us for a <hi>proof</hi> of what we hold not: but fear not our deſign, your <hi>Infallibility</hi> will ſecure you from ſo pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable a <hi>Cheat.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I, for my part, cannot conſent to leave out that word, becauſe it is not <hi>fair</hi> to alter a word of Dr. <hi>St.</hi>'s; nor <hi>poſſible,</hi> though it were <hi>fair.</hi> For you and I cannot make him not to have ſaid what he hath ſaid; and though we ſhould agree to ſuppreſs that word amongſt our ſelves, it will ſtill be found in his two <hi>Letters,</hi> do what we can. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>There let it ſtand. When you diſpute with <hi>him,</hi> agree on what terms you can; but 'tis not <hi>fair</hi> in a diſcourſe with <hi>me,</hi> who have nothing to do with the <hi>Conference</hi> or his <hi>Letters,</hi> to make me <hi>ſay</hi> what you pleaſe, and then bid me <hi>prove</hi> it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Now we are thus far onward, 'tis pity to break for a ſingle word. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>certainty</hi> then that we have of the holy <hi>Scripture,</hi> which we acknowledge to be our <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> we manifeſt after the ſame manner as you do <hi>yours. A. p .</hi> 8.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>As we do our <hi>Rule,</hi> or <hi>Scripture?</hi> I know not which you mean. <hi>R. p.</hi> 14.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Your certainty</hi> of the <hi>Scripture</hi> I mean.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Do not you remember that <hi>Abſolute certainty of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> is not the point to be proved, though I told you ſo in the very page you cite? <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I remember you told us ſo: And I remember too, that you told us, <hi>p.</hi> 22. <hi>That to prove it in our way, we would find it a hard task.</hi> Therefore I thought fit to tell you only, that <hi>our way of proof</hi> is the very ſame with <hi>yours,</hi> and ſo no harder a task for <hi>us</hi> than <hi>you.</hi> 'Twas <hi>you</hi> undertook to <hi>ſhew the Nullity of our Rule of Faith,</hi> which is <hi>Scripture:</hi> I knew by that, that the <hi>certainty of Scripture</hi> is not the point to be <hi>prov'd</hi> by <hi>me;</hi> but the <hi>Nullity</hi> of it, the point to be <hi>proved</hi> by <hi>you.</hi> And you might have remember'd, that I had ſaid in the ſame place, <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>That you yielded our certainty of Scripture;</hi> and yet you again,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65387:11"/>like a man <hi>well awake,</hi> ask me if I do not remember what I have told you I do remember.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>But pray how do you <hi>prove</hi> that which is the <hi>point? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>That which is the <hi>point,</hi> is to be <hi>proved</hi> by <hi>you,</hi> who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook in your <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> to <hi>prove</hi> it. I only told you again, that it being granted us that <hi>Scripture</hi> is <hi>God's Word,</hi> we think that we ſufficiently prove the <hi>certainty</hi> of <hi>every Article</hi> of our <hi>Faith,</hi> when we ſhew it to be ſolidly grounded on that <hi>Word. A. p.</hi> 9.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>We are not ſo far yet; it will be time to talk of <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that Article,</hi> when <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that Article</hi> comes in queſtion <hi>R.p.</hi> 15.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I went not about to prove <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that Article,</hi> but only told you how we thought they might be <hi>proved.</hi> If it be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>certainty</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> which is our <hi>Rule,</hi> nor of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> which are our <hi>Faith,</hi> what is it, I pray, you would have us <hi>prove,</hi> when it comes to our <hi>turn</hi> to prove?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>At preſent you are to ſhew, that you have any means, unleſs you take <hi>ours,</hi> to ground any <hi>Article</hi> ſolidly on the <hi>Word of God.</hi> You are to ſhew your <hi>interpretation</hi> of it is <hi>abſolutely certain,</hi> and that <hi>God's Word</hi> means as you teach it does. <hi>R.p.</hi> 15.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>queſtion</hi> at preſent is, about the <hi>certainty</hi> of our <hi>Rule</hi> the <hi>Scripture,</hi> which you undertook to prove <hi>null.</hi> When you have proved it <hi>null,</hi> it will be <hi>vain</hi> and <hi>idle</hi> to diſpute about the <hi>means</hi> of <hi>underſtanding</hi> it; and now that you have but <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken</hi> it only, 'tis <hi>unſeaſonable</hi> to require of us to ſhew the <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain means</hi> of <hi>underſtanding</hi> it, before you have made good your <hi>undertaking.</hi> I hope it may therefore now ſuffice to tell you, That we both have and uſe all the <hi>means</hi> which God hath leſt us for that purpoſe, and they are the very ſame again that the men of <hi>your Church</hi> uſe, not omitting <hi>Tradition</hi> (which I ſuppoſe is it you call <hi>yours</hi>) ſo far as it can be of any <hi>uſe</hi> to us. Our <hi>Articles</hi> (as I told you, <hi>A.p.</hi> 9.) are <hi>yours</hi> too, contain'd in thoſe very <hi>Creeds</hi> which <hi>you</hi> receive, and all proved by your <hi>own Writers,</hi> yea and <hi>Councils</hi> too, to be ſolidly grounded on
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65387:12"/>
                  <hi>Scripture,</hi> no otherwiſe than we prove them to be. What <hi>more</hi> do you deſire? Two things <hi>more</hi> you would have us prove: Firſt, <hi>That we are abſolutely certain of all this:</hi> And ſecondly, <hi>Not only</hi> of this, <hi>but of all that</hi> more <hi>which our Saviour taught his Apoſtles.</hi> But we are not obliged to <hi>prove</hi> either of theſe. <hi>Ap.</hi> 9.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Dr. <hi>St.</hi> did affirm, that you are <hi>abſolutely certain</hi> of <hi>all this,</hi> and of <hi>all this</hi> I demand <hi>proof. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>What Dr. <hi>St.</hi> affirm'd is nothing to me, till I know in what ſence he affirm'd it, which I am to learn (when it concerns me) of <hi>himſelf,</hi> and not of <hi>you.</hi> I therefore abſtain from the word <hi>[abſolutely]</hi> becauſe you take it to be the ſame with <hi>[in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly].</hi> Whatever <hi>proof</hi> therefore you may demand of <hi>him</hi> for it, you ought not to demand any of <hi>me.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>All mankind made <hi>abſolutely certain</hi> and <hi>infallible</hi> all one, before I was born. And yet you would perſwade us I break the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Diſputation</hi> by underſtanding that word us every body does. <hi>R. p.</hi> 16.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>How every body underſtood <hi>words</hi> before you were born, I pretend not to know; nor ſay I, you break the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Diſputation</hi> by ſo <hi>underſtanding</hi> the <hi>word,</hi> but by <hi>impoſing</hi> on me a <hi>proof</hi> of what I <hi>affirm'd not.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I would be glad to know how your ſelf take it, who to be ſure take it right. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I never <hi>uſed</hi> it, and therefore am not concern'd to tell you how I <hi>take</hi> it. But if any <hi>Proteſtant</hi> affirm himſelf <hi>abſolutely cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> I muſt think (how <hi>improperly</hi> ſoever he may <hi>ſpeak</hi>) that he means not he is <hi>infallible,</hi> but as <hi>certain</hi> as a man <hi>can</hi> or <hi>needs</hi> to be, and without all juſt <hi>cauſe</hi> of <hi>doubting.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>With all then that a man can get here, he may be <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. R. p.</hi> 17.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis <hi>poſſible</hi> he <hi>may,</hi> but there is no <hi>cauſe</hi> to <hi>imagine</hi> he <hi>is;</hi> 'tis honeſter dealing to perſwade men to reſt ſatisfied with that meaſure of <hi>certainty</hi> their condition admits, than to tempt them (as you know who did) to think they ſhall be as <hi>Gods, infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:65387:12"/>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>ſecond</hi> part of your charge is purely your own <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention,</hi> and as pleaſant an Invention as ever roving <hi>Fancy</hi> ſuggeſted. <hi>R. p.</hi> 17.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis ſpoken ſo like <hi>your ſelf,</hi> Sir, that I cannot be angry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You <hi>faucy</hi> I would have you ſay, you are <hi>certain</hi> of thoſe <hi>points,</hi> which you deny to be in <hi>Scripture,</hi> and think them to be added by the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent;</hi> and which therefore you <hi>believe</hi> not. And theſe <hi>points</hi> you underſtand by the <hi>[were]</hi> of which I demanded <hi>proof.—Ridiculous Folly!</hi> to pretend we expected <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſhould <hi>prove</hi> to us ſuch <hi>points</hi> as they <hi>denied,</hi> and our ſelves <hi>held,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Good ſtill. <hi>You</hi> will not give me leave to <hi>laugh,</hi> and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get leave of <hi>my ſelf</hi> to be <hi>angry.</hi> Pray tell me once again, What is it you expect we ſhould prove?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Your <hi>abſolute certainty</hi> of the <hi>[more]</hi> which you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve beſides this, that <hi>Scripture is Scripture. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>That <hi>Scripture is Scripture,</hi> is as <hi>ſelf-evident</hi> as that <hi>a Rule is a Rule.</hi> That it is the <hi>Word of God,</hi> may be <hi>proved,</hi> and it hath been <hi>granted.</hi> What we believe <hi>more,</hi> I told you we prove from plain places of <hi>Scripture</hi> wherein it is contain'd; and we we the more <hi>confirm'd</hi> in our <hi>Faith</hi> by the <hi>teſtimony</hi> and <hi>conſent</hi> of the <hi>Primitive Church</hi> in the <hi>Creeds</hi> eſpecially. Will this <hi>proof</hi> ſatisfie? Then we have ſufficiently proved <hi>all</hi> the <hi>more</hi> we believe; and could you thus prove <hi>all</hi> the <hi>more</hi> you believe, your <hi>whole Faith</hi> ſhould be <hi>ours</hi> too. If it ſuffice not, I would ſain know why your <hi>Trent Council</hi> called the <hi>Nicene Creed, That Principle wherein all that profeſs the Faith of Chriſt, neceſſarily agree, and the from and only foundation againſt which the gater of Hell ſhall not prevail.</hi> What, I pray, was the <hi>First Queſtion</hi> at the <hi>Conference?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Whether <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are <hi>abſolutely certain</hi> that they hold now the <hi>ſame</hi> Tenets in <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> that our Saviour taught his Apoſtles. <hi>L. p.</hi> 6.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>What we <hi>believe,</hi> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>Scripture;</hi> and what is contain'd in <hi>Scripture,</hi> is that which Chriſt and his Apoſtles
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65387:13"/>taught. We hold them the <hi>ſame Tenets</hi> in <hi>Faith</hi> which Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught. Is this enough?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Prove that you hold the <hi>ſame,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> they taught.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>If the <hi>ſame</hi> that is <hi>contain'd</hi> in <hi>Scripture</hi> be <hi>all</hi> they taught. I have ſhew'd you how we prove we believe <hi>all.</hi> If that <hi>ſame</hi> be not <hi>all,</hi> then in bidding us prove we are <hi>certain</hi> of <hi>all,</hi> you bid us prove we are <hi>certain</hi> of <hi>more than is contain'd in Scripture,</hi> that is, what <hi>you hold,</hi> and what <hi>we believe not,</hi> but <hi>deny.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You <hi>fancy</hi> I would have you ſay, you are <hi>certain</hi> of <hi>all</hi> thoſe <hi>points</hi> which <hi>you deny</hi> to be in <hi>Scripture,</hi> and think them to be <hi>added</hi> by the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I had ſaid (<hi>A. p.</hi> 11.) we have <hi>certainty</hi> of <hi>all</hi> that is taught us in <hi>Scripture,</hi> and we know of no <hi>more</hi> that Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught. That <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay there is <hi>more,</hi> and that we are bound to <hi>believe</hi> it. And hence I <hi>fancy,</hi> that before you can oblige us to ſay we are <hi>certain</hi> of, or to believe <hi>all this more,</hi> it is your part to <hi>prove</hi> it. <hi>Ridiculous Folly!</hi> ſay you. Why? That a man ſhould not be <hi>obliged</hi> to <hi>believe</hi> a thing, till it be diſcover'd to him. Sir, I know very well, you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect not we ſhould <hi>prove</hi> to you ſuch points as <hi>we deny,</hi> and <hi>you hold:</hi> But do not you think, becauſe we cannot prove them, we ought therefore to confeſs we are not <hi>certain</hi> that we believe <hi>all</hi> that Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught? Do you hold no <hi>more</hi> but what is contain'd in <hi>Scripture?</hi> If <hi>no more,</hi> ſhew us <hi>all</hi> your <hi>Trentine Faith</hi> there, and we will believe it too: But if <hi>more,</hi> either you hold <hi>more</hi> than Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles taught, or <hi>all</hi> they taught is not contain'd in <hi>Scripture.</hi> If the <hi>former</hi> be true, you will confeſs we are not bound to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> that <hi>more;</hi> if the <hi>later,</hi> you bid us <hi>prove</hi> what <hi>we deny</hi> and <hi>you hold,</hi> and <hi>ſay</hi> we are <hi>certain</hi> of <hi>all</hi> this, that is, <hi>more</hi> than is contain'd in <hi>Scripture,</hi> and what we <hi>believe</hi> not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You talk indeed of <hi>Proof,</hi> and that which you ſay of it is, That you <hi>prove</hi> when you <hi>prove. R. p.</hi> 19.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I have told you how we <hi>prove</hi> the <hi>Scripture</hi> to be the <hi>Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:65387:13"/>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Which, if one ſhould put you to it, you cannot. <hi>R. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Which when we would do, you ſay it <hi>needs not,</hi> nor ought you to <hi>allow</hi> it, <hi>L. p.</hi> 22. We ſhew alſo how we <hi>prove</hi> every <hi>Article</hi> of our <hi>Faith</hi> by <hi>Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Common words,</hi> which every <hi>Heretick</hi> may and does uſe. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>But no <hi>common work,</hi> which every <hi>Heretick</hi> may or can do. Yet when we offer to do it, you tell us <hi>'tis not time</hi> to do it yet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You decline Dr. <hi>St.</hi>'s <hi>abſolute certainty,</hi> nor know of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way to prove more than a <hi>ſufficient certainty. R. p.</hi> 20.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Dr. <hi>St.</hi>'s <hi>abſolute certainty</hi> I gueſs to be no more than <hi>ſufficient certainty,</hi> and if ſo, I decline it not, when 'tis my <hi>turn</hi> to <hi>prove.</hi> What's <hi>ſufficient,</hi> is certainly <hi>enough,</hi> and your <hi>abſolute certainty</hi> or <hi>infallibility</hi> I decline, becauſe it is <hi>too much.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>This <hi>ſufficient certainty</hi> of yours may be <hi>no certainty. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>That's abſolutely impoſſible; for <hi>no certainty</hi> is neither <hi>certainty</hi> nor <hi>ſufficient.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>There goes no more to make a thing <hi>ſufficient,</hi> than to make a man <hi>content</hi> with it. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Juſt ſo much <hi>more</hi> as will enable him to obtain the <hi>end</hi> for which he <hi>hath</hi> it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>A yard of Cloath will make a <hi>ſufficient</hi> Garment for him who is <hi>content</hi> to go <hi>half naked. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, if he have a mind to <hi>catch cold</hi> and <hi>die.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>A Table without Meat, is a <hi>ſufficient</hi> Meal for him that is <hi>contented</hi> to <hi>fast. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>How a <hi>naked Table</hi> can be a <hi>Meal,</hi> I know not: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, it is not always a <hi>ſufficient Meal</hi> for a <hi>Faſting Papist,</hi> though a <hi>Table</hi> without <hi>Wine</hi> may ſeem enough for a <hi>Feast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> one. You told me your <hi>abſolute certainty</hi> and <hi>infallibility</hi> would come into <hi>play</hi> again ere long. Now you <hi>play</hi> indeed, and to tell you truly, I am quite weary on't.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="dialogue">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:65387:14"/>
            <head>The Second Dialogue.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I Will let you ſee in a ſhort <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> how far your <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> is from being <hi>abſolutely certain. L. p.</hi> 30.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Far enough, if you ſhew what you undertook to ſhew, the <hi>Nullity</hi> of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>My <hi>first</hi> Propoſition is this: <hi>God has left us ſome way to know ſurely what Christ and his Apoſtles taught. R. p.</hi> 2.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Your <hi>Propoſition</hi> is granted, what now infer you from it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Therefore <hi>this way, must be ſuch, that they who take it ſhall arrive by it at the end it was intended for, that is, know ſurely what Christ and his Apoſtles taught. L. p.</hi> 30.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>If God have left us a way to know, then by that way we may know.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You muſt needs be wording on't your <hi>own</hi> way, to <hi>ſhew</hi> that either you did not <hi>underſtand</hi> it, or that you had a mind to inform us how neatly and dexterouſly you can <hi>change</hi> and <hi>pervert</hi> words, as well as <hi>anſwer. R. p.</hi> 21.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Where have I <hi>changed</hi> or <hi>perverted</hi> your words?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Is <hi>ſhall</hi> know, and <hi>may</hi> know, all one? <hi>R. p.</hi> 22.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>They are not the ſame word indeed, and I now confeſs I did put <hi>may</hi> for <hi>ſhall</hi> not in your ſaying, but my own. And if I had done it <hi>wittingly,</hi> to <hi>ſhew</hi> either my <hi>Ignorance</hi> or my <hi>Art,</hi> little reaſon could you have to be angry with ſo courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous an <hi>Adverſary,</hi> who was willing to ſacrifice the <hi>credit</hi> of his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> or <hi>Sincerity,</hi> as according to you I muſt have been to your ſervice. But to ſay truth, I was not ſo kind; neither over obſerved I the <hi>change</hi> I had made, till you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd me. I beg your pardon for this error, and have more cauſe to thank you for minding me of it, than it may be you thought of giving me. Let it therefore be <hi>ſhall,</hi> what mean you by it more than <hi>may?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shall,</hi> that is, <hi>cannot chuſe but know. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I confeſs I took them for terms <hi>equivalent,</hi> as they are
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65387:14"/>often uſed, and therefore I <hi>granted all</hi> as true, thô I could not but ſmile at the <hi>Argument,</hi> which, as I underſtood it, proved only the <hi>ſame</hi> by the <hi>ſame,</hi> that is, nothing at all. But now you have diſcover'd my <hi>Error,</hi> you have ſpoiled my <hi>Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> too, as you call it, for what through <hi>Error</hi> was <hi>granted</hi> to <hi>your advantage,</hi> I muſt now <hi>deny,</hi> I mean the <hi>conſequence,</hi> and my reaſon is, (in the words you have taught me) <hi>becauſe you cannot draw Beer out of a Jarr of Oyl.</hi> More is in the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion</hi> than in the <hi>Premiſes.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I make account the <hi>Way</hi> to know the <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is not a <hi>right Way,</hi> if thoſe who take it <hi>can</hi> fail to know their <hi>Faith,</hi> and therefore not the <hi>Way</hi> left by God. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot yet paſs your <hi>account,</hi> for you have ſaid your ſelf, (<hi>L. p.</hi> 15.) <hi>that they who both take and follow the</hi> Way <hi>may leave it again.</hi> You ſpake of <hi>Tradition</hi> the <hi>only Way,</hi> as you will have it left by <hi>God.</hi> Hence, by your own confeſſion, I think it may be inferred, that the <hi>Way</hi> may be <hi>right,</hi> and yet they that <hi>take</hi> it miſtake in the <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You barely ſay We <hi>may</hi> know, with which it conſiſts, We <hi>may not</hi> know; and ſo you make us a <hi>Way,</hi> in which they who <hi>travel</hi> may be always out of the <hi>Way. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>This ſeems a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> too childiſh. I ſay not <hi>that's</hi> the <hi>Way</hi> in which they that <hi>travel</hi> may be always <hi>out of</hi> the <hi>way,</hi> but out of which they may <hi>wander,</hi> and then they <hi>travel</hi> not in it, but are <hi>out</hi> of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scripture's Letter, Interpretable by Private Judgments, is not that Way.</hi> L. p. 30.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Whom do you here <hi>diſpute</hi> againſt? If againſt <hi>us,</hi> why do you not in terms <hi>contradict</hi> our <hi>Doctrine? A. p.</hi> 12.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Two very pleaſant <hi>Queſtions. R. p.</hi> 22.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I hope then we ſhall have two as pleaſant <hi>Anſwers.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Your <hi>own,</hi> and my <hi>Title-page</hi> tells you, I am diſputing againſt the D. of <hi>P's. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>They do ſo. I had reaſon therefore to fear you had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got your ſelf becauſe you did not <hi>contradict</hi> his <hi>Tenet.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:65387:15"/>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>To ask, why I do not uſe <hi>Terms</hi> to your mind, is to ask, why the <hi>Defendant</hi> does not go to the <hi>Plaintiff</hi> to draw his <hi>Anſwer. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>An Anſwer <hi>pleaſant</hi> enough. But pray ſay, if an <hi>Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent</hi> ought not to prove the <hi>contradictory Propoſition</hi> to that which the <hi>Anſwerer defends?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I have happen'd to <hi>propoſe</hi> firſt what I <hi>intended</hi> to prove, before I <hi>go about</hi> to prove it, which I thought was the cleareſt way, and you will needs ſpeak to my <hi>concluſion</hi> before you ſpeak to the <hi>premiſes. R. p.</hi> 23.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>And I have happened to ſay, that what you have <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd</hi> to be proved, is not the <hi>Propoſition</hi> to be proved; and you quarrel with me for ſpeaking to your <hi>concluſion</hi> before your <hi>premiſes,</hi> whilſt there are yet neither <hi>premiſes</hi> nor <hi>concluſion.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhall mind only the <hi>Proof</hi> here, and reſerve the <hi>Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> till I come to the place where I make it. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>If you will needs <hi>prove</hi> what we <hi>deny</hi> not, as we cannot <hi>help</hi> it, ſo can we not be <hi>concern'd</hi> in it. But take your own way, I muſt not hinder your <hi>courſe,</hi> whoſe buſineſs you have made it only to <hi>trace</hi> you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>We experience <hi>Presbyterians <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Socinians</hi> both take that <hi>way,</hi> yet differ in ſuch high <hi>Fundamentals,</hi> as the <hi>Trinity</hi> and the <hi>Godhead</hi> of <hi>Chriſt. L. p.</hi> 30.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>The force of your <hi>Argument</hi> ſeems this. <hi>If any men can be found, who wrest or miſinterpret</hi> Scripture, <hi>then can it not be the</hi> way <hi>to know what</hi> Chriſt <hi>and his</hi> Apoſtles <hi>taught.</hi> And muſt a <hi>Rule</hi> be therefore no <hi>good Rule,</hi> becauſe ſome who <hi>uſe</hi> it, <hi>miſunderſtand</hi> or <hi>abuſe</hi> it? <hi>A. p.</hi> 15.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>What may you mean by this? <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I ſay the <hi>miſunderſtanding</hi> or <hi>abuſing</hi> of any <hi>Rule,</hi> does not <hi>change</hi> the <hi>Rule</hi> it ſelf into a <hi>bad</hi> or <hi>wrong Rule,</hi> if it was a <hi>good</hi> and <hi>right Rule</hi> before, or <hi>prove</hi> that it was <hi>not</hi> ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I take my <hi>Ruler</hi> and draw a <hi>Line</hi> by it; does the <hi>crookedneſs</hi> or <hi>ſtraightneſs</hi> of this <hi>Line</hi> depend upon my <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:65387:15"/>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>To what end this talk of a <hi>Ruler</hi> and a <hi>Line</hi> can come in here I know not; a <hi>ſcrupulous</hi> man would be apt to fear you were now in good earneſt about to <hi>ſhew</hi> the <hi>Nullity</hi> of our <hi>Rule</hi> by a <hi>Mathematical Demonſtration,</hi> ſeeing you have got your <hi>Ruler</hi> in your hand. We ſhall ſee I hope anon what 'twill come to. Now to your <hi>Queſtion.</hi> Tho' the <hi>crookedneſs</hi> or <hi>ſtraightneſs</hi> of the <hi>Line</hi> depend not <hi>only</hi> on your <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> yet <hi>partly</hi> it may. He that <hi>underſtands</hi> not the <hi>uſe</hi> of his <hi>Ruler</hi> may draw wrong by it. It is no news to ſee a Boy <hi>Rule</hi> a whole <hi>Page</hi> with a ſtraight <hi>Ruler,</hi> and yet make never a <hi>Line ſtraight.</hi> Many things elſe may alſo cauſe the <hi>crookedneſs</hi> of the <hi>Line.</hi> Your <hi>drawing</hi> hand may <hi>ſhake,</hi> your <hi>holding</hi> hand may <hi>ſlip,</hi> you may have <hi>had eyes,</hi> or be <hi>careleſs, drouzy,</hi> or <hi>drunk.</hi> However, let the <hi>Line</hi> prove as it will, the <hi>Rule</hi> is ſtraight whether you <hi>underſtand</hi> how to <hi>draw</hi> by it or no, which is that I affirm'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>If you make the <hi>Letter</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> your <hi>Rule,</hi> and ſo <hi>Private interpreting</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſing</hi> of it, and the <hi>Sence</hi> the <hi>Line drawn;</hi> unriddle to us, if you can, how the <hi>Sence</hi> drawn from the <hi>Letter</hi> can any more fail to be <hi>true,</hi> than the <hi>Line</hi> drawn by the <hi>Rule</hi> to be <hi>ſtraight;</hi> and which way that <hi>Sence</hi> can be <hi>miſunderſtood,</hi> and how the <hi>Rule</hi> can be a <hi>good Rule,</hi> if it be <hi>uſed,</hi> and the <hi>Sence</hi> to which it is a <hi>Rule</hi> be <hi>miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood? R. p.</hi> 25.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Had you ſuffer'd me to ſpeak to your <hi>Propoſition.</hi> I had poſſibly prevented all this your ſpeaking to no purpoſe. But you are in haſte to <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> I <hi>ſay</hi> what I do <hi>not</hi> ſay, and then will tie me to <hi>unriddle</hi> all that <hi>you ſay.</hi> 'Tis, if you would know, the <hi>Letter</hi> with the <hi>Sence</hi> that is our <hi>Rule;</hi> our <hi>learning</hi> it, and <hi>comparing</hi> Doctrines with it, is our uſing it; our <hi>Belief</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> are the <hi>Lines</hi> drawn from or by it. And now ſet your <hi>Fancy</hi> a working again for a new <hi>Riddle</hi> if you pleaſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>A <hi>Grammar Rule,</hi> let it be never ſo <hi>ill underſtood,</hi> will make good <hi>conſtruction</hi> in caſe it be <hi>uſed;</hi> ſo the <hi>Scripture-Rule,</hi> if it be, as you put it, <hi>uſed,</hi> muſt needs produce right <hi>ſence. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:65387:16"/>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Where did I put it barely, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſed,</hi> or where ſaid I, it would produce right <hi>Sence?</hi> Here's no <hi>falſifying!</hi> Did you indeed, Sir, never make falſe <hi>Latine</hi> by <hi>miſunderſtanding</hi> your <hi>Rule?</hi> or did your <hi>Maſter</hi> then tell you, that a <hi>Grammar Rule,</hi> let it be never ſo <hi>ill underſtood,</hi> would make good <hi>conſtruction,</hi> in caſe it be <hi>uſed,</hi> and therefore the <hi>Rule</hi> by <hi>miſunderſtanding</hi> whereof you made <hi>bad conſtruction</hi> was no <hi>good Rule?</hi> Or was it <hi>you</hi> that made <hi>falſe Latine,</hi> whileſt the <hi>Rule</hi> being <hi>uſed</hi> by you made <hi>true?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The truth is, a <hi>Grammar Rule</hi> is not a <hi>Rule</hi> till it be <hi>underſtood. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Then no <hi>School-boy</hi> can <hi>miſunderſtand</hi> his <hi>Rule;</hi> and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>School boy makes</hi> his <hi>Grammar</hi> by <hi>learning</hi> it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>He that <hi>underſtands</hi> not what 'tis, for <hi>Nominative Caſes</hi> and <hi>Verbs</hi> to agree, has no <hi>Rule</hi> to make them agree. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Not in his <hi>underſtanding,</hi> but ſurely in his <hi>Grammar</hi> he hath, or he goes to <hi>School</hi> in vain to <hi>learn</hi> it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You will make the <hi>Letter</hi> of <hi>Scripture first under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood</hi> to be the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>underſtanding</hi> it. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>We make the <hi>Letter</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> having plain <hi>Sence</hi> and <hi>intelligible</hi> the <hi>Rule</hi> of our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> it, and being <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood</hi> the <hi>Rule</hi> of our <hi>Belief.</hi> But when you ſay a <hi>Rule</hi> is no <hi>Rule</hi> 'till it be <hi>underſtood,</hi> do not you make <hi>Tradition first underſtood</hi> the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> it? If not, by what other <hi>Rule</hi> do you <hi>underſtand</hi> it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You <hi>Queſtion</hi> on. Muſt a <hi>Way</hi> be a <hi>wrong Way,</hi> becauſe ſome that <hi>take</hi> it will not <hi>keep</hi> it? Riddle my Riddle again. <hi>R. p.</hi> 26.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>More <hi>Riddles</hi> ſtill? Well, let's have 'em.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Pray who are or can be thoſe ſome who <hi>take</hi> it and will not keep it? <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>The very ſame, who (as you have told me) at one time <hi>follow</hi> it, and at another <hi>leave</hi> it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>As long as they <hi>take</hi> it, they <hi>keep</hi> it, I think. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>And when they <hi>leave</hi> it, they <hi>keep</hi> it <hi>not,</hi> I am ſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:65387:16"/>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>He who has no will to <hi>keep</hi> it, may when he pleaſes go <hi>out</hi> of it, but then he does no longer <hi>take</hi> it, and is none of the ſome of whom the <hi>Queſtion</hi> ſpeaks. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>So may he that has no <hi>care</hi> to <hi>keep</hi> it, go out of it when he <hi>conſiders</hi> it not. Yet are they both the ſame of whom the <hi>Queſtion</hi> was (if it was not impertinent) who firſt <hi>took</hi> it, and after <hi>went out</hi> of it, and then <hi>kept</hi> it <hi>not.</hi> You ask, Who <hi>can</hi> do this? You anſwer, Whoever will <hi>may</hi> do it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>He that <hi>takes</hi> the <hi>Way,</hi> ſhall <hi>certainly</hi> arrive at his Journey's end, let him <hi>will</hi> what he pleaſes, and the <hi>way</hi> muſt needs be a wrong <hi>way</hi> if he do not. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yea! Thô he <hi>will</hi> go <hi>out</hi> of it? And is the <hi>way</hi> a <hi>wrong way</hi> when he goes <hi>out</hi> of it? Doth a man's <hi>taking</hi> or <hi>leaving</hi> a <hi>Way</hi> make it <hi>right</hi> or <hi>wrong?</hi> This I imagine is it you would have. The <hi>way</hi> is <hi>Right</hi> that <hi>you take,</hi> and <hi>Wrong</hi> that <hi>you leave;</hi> and ſo we need not ask for the <hi>Right way,</hi> but which <hi>Way you go,</hi> and that to be ſure is <hi>right.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You imagine we are talking of one, who only <hi>takes</hi> the <hi>Way</hi> at firſt, and after <hi>leaves</hi> it. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>If you talk of one that <hi>takes</hi> it and cannot <hi>leave</hi> it, you talk of no body that I know, and ſo may talk on for me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The Argument proceeds of ſuch as make the way their <hi>choice,</hi> and <hi>perſiſt</hi> to follow no other to their lives end. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It proceeds of thoſe whom you ſuppoſe to <hi>err</hi> in <hi>Faith,</hi> and if it be <hi>true</hi> which you ſuppoſe, thô they may pretend to chuſe the <hi>Scripture</hi> for their <hi>Rule,</hi> they do not indeed <hi>follow</hi> it, In ſhort, till it be proved that God hath left ſuch a <hi>Way</hi> or <hi>Rule,</hi> as no man can poſſibly <hi>err out</hi> of it, <hi>miſtake</hi> it or <hi>abuſe</hi> it; and that it is not enough that he hath left us ſuch a <hi>Way</hi> or <hi>Rule,</hi> as men may <hi>underſtand</hi> and <hi>obſerve,</hi> if they be not wanting to themſelves; it will not follow, that the <hi>Scripture's Letter,</hi> as we own it, is not the <hi>Way,</hi> thô not only <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians,</hi> but the greater number of Mankind ſhould <hi>own</hi> it, and yet differ about <hi>Fundamental</hi> Points contained in it. <hi>A. p.</hi> 15, 16.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:65387:17"/>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>As many as leave the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> leave the <hi>Way</hi> left by God; and you, like a right <hi>pleaſant</hi> man, would have it prov'd, that the thing cannot poſſibly be done, which we ſee is done by Millions; and would have us, who ſay they all do <hi>err</hi> and <hi>miſtake,</hi> to prove they cannot. <hi>R. p.</hi> 27.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I ſay nothing now of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> but asle if it be not as <hi>pleaſant</hi> in you, to ſuppoſe me to bid you prove it, becauſe I ſay till it be <hi>proved,</hi> which I grant it can never be, your <hi>Argument's</hi> naught?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Will it not follow, that the <hi>Way</hi> by which, a man that goes in it, comes to <hi>Error;</hi> is not the <hi>Way</hi> to <hi>Truth? R. p.</hi> 28.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>If the <hi>Way lead</hi> him into <hi>Error,</hi> it is not the <hi>Way</hi> to <hi>Truth.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Since <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Socinians</hi> both <hi>Interpret Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> by their <hi>own Judgments,</hi> and one ſide knows not the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> it follows unavoidably, that the <hi>Way</hi> of <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Interpretation</hi> is no ſure <hi>Way</hi> to know it. <hi>R. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scripture</hi> we affirm to be the <hi>Rule,</hi> you will prove <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's Letter Interpretable,</hi> &amp;c. is not the Rule, and at laſt conclude, <hi>Private Interpretation is not the Rule.</hi> What's all this to us? You have thus Hackney'd out a pair of <hi>Metaphors</hi> (<hi>Way</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi>) to courſe it on all four (which no <hi>Metaphor</hi> can do) ſo long after your nimble <hi>Fancy,</hi> till you have quite <hi>jaded</hi> them, and then you would turn them up to us for <hi>Riddles.</hi> No, Sir, take them as you have uſed them, and let them reſt at <hi>Private Interpretation,</hi> for <hi>Scripture</hi> has no longer any room for them <hi>ſo uſed.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>What do you talk of <hi>erring,</hi> or <hi>miſtaking</hi> the <hi>Way?</hi> 'Tis true, theſe erring men miſtake the <hi>true Way,</hi> but they mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake not the <hi>Way</hi> which you <hi>call</hi> the <hi>true Way. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>If they err (as you ſuppoſe) they miſtake what we <hi>call</hi> the <hi>true Way,</hi> the <hi>Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>They <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> by their <hi>Private Judgment,</hi> and ſo <hi>take</hi> not <hi>miſtake, uſe</hi> not <hi>abuſe</hi> it. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Private-Interpretation</hi> you muſt mean by <hi>It.</hi> for that is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65387:17"/>it which you would make us <hi>call</hi> the <hi>true Way,</hi> though it be not. <hi>Scripture</hi> is the <hi>true Way,</hi> and their <hi>private interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is their <hi>abuſe</hi> of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Sure you mean, they miſtake the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of Chriſt, and ſo by miſtaking the <hi>Way,</hi> you wiſely underſtand miſtaking the <hi>Eud. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Doctrine</hi> of Chriſt in the <hi>Scripture</hi> is the <hi>Way</hi> to a right <hi>Faith,</hi> and by miſtaking that <hi>Way,</hi> they err in <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>To what purpoſe do you tell us that men may <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand</hi> and <hi>obſerve</hi> (as if <hi>obſerving</hi> concern'd our queſtion of <hi>knowing</hi>) if they be not wanting to themſelves? <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>A rare kind of <hi>knowledge</hi> it is that comes without <hi>obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</hi> Should <hi>we</hi> not <hi>obſerve</hi> what <hi>you</hi> ſay, we ſhould <hi>anſwer</hi> you as you <hi>defire,</hi> without <hi>knowing</hi> your <hi>craft.</hi> It is ſure to ſome purpoſe, to tell of <hi>underſtanding a Rule,</hi> and <hi>obſerving</hi> or <hi>keeping</hi> (ſo I meant) a <hi>way.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>They who take a <hi>right way,</hi> not only <hi>may,</hi> but <hi>must,</hi> and cannot poſſibly <hi>fail</hi> of coming whither it leads.—Men have no more to do with a <hi>way,</hi> but to <hi>travel</hi> in it, and ſo can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>wanting to themſelves</hi> in that reſpect, if they do. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Men have not ſo much to do, it ſeems, as to <hi>obſerve</hi> the <hi>Way;</hi> but as long as they trot on any how, all's well enough.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Of the ſame batch is your <hi>not underſtanding,</hi> and <hi>not keeping</hi> a <hi>Way.</hi> As if they who <hi>interpret</hi> by their <hi>private Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> did not <hi>keep</hi> the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>interpreting by private Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. R. p.</hi> 29.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>As if the <hi>way</hi> or <hi>Rule</hi> to be <hi>interpreted,</hi> and the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>interpreting</hi> were all one. Or as if by keeping his <hi>own way</hi> of <hi>interpreting</hi> a man may not <hi>mif-interpret</hi> or <hi>wiſ-underſtand,</hi> or go out of the <hi>right way.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Yet that very <hi>miſ-underſtanding</hi> is their <hi>underſtanding</hi> it to be the <hi>Way,</hi> and ſo they, even in your opinion, <hi>miſ-under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not</hi> the <hi>Way,</hi> however they <hi>miſ-underſtand</hi> by it. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Here's a <hi>Riddle</hi> indeed! Might not all this <hi>confuſion</hi> and <hi>blundring</hi> have been avoided, might I have ſet your <hi>Propoſition</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:65387:18"/>right at firſt? But ſo you had loſt your <hi>advantage</hi> of traveling in the <hi>dark,</hi> leſt your <hi>Errors</hi> ſhould be too eaſily <hi>diſcovered.</hi> They <hi>underſtand Scripture</hi> to be the <hi>Way,</hi> yet cannot their <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtanding</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> be their <hi>underſtanding it</hi> to be ſo, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>miſ-underſtanding</hi> and <hi>right underſtanding</hi> be all one. And ſo, in my opinion, <hi>underſtanding Scripture</hi> to be the <hi>Way,</hi> they may yet <hi>miſ-underſtand</hi> it, but not <hi>miſ-underſtand</hi> by it.</p>
               <p>I told you, <hi>It follows no more that</hi> Scripture <hi>is not the</hi> Way, <hi>becauſe men that own it differ about matters contained in it, than it follows, that becauſe we ſee men miſ-interpret and break good</hi> Laws <hi>daily, therefore thoſe</hi> Laws <hi>are unintelligible, or cannot be kept, and must be thought inſufficient to ſhew what the Lawgiver expects from them. R. p.</hi> 16.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>What <hi>breaking</hi> and <hi>keeping Laws</hi> is brought in for, you beſt know that bring them in. <hi>R. p.</hi> 29.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I brought them in to ſhew, that a <hi>Rule</hi> may be <hi>intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> and <hi>ſufficient,</hi> though ſome men <hi>miſ-interpret</hi> or <hi>break</hi> it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Our Diſcourſe is only about knowing the Doctrine of <hi>Faith,</hi> and not at all about living up to it, and ſo hath nothing to do with thoſe who know, but will not keep the <hi>Laws. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yet if the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>living</hi> be no leſs a <hi>true Rule</hi> for being <hi>miſ-interpreted,</hi> why muſt the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> be for that <hi>no true Rule?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You end your <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> very ſuitably to the reſt, with an <hi>inſtance</hi> directly againſt your ſelf. You ſee that <hi>Laws</hi> left to <hi>private interpretation</hi> are by all mankind judg'd <hi>inſufficient,</hi> and <hi>publick Interpreters</hi> therefore ſet up every-where; and from the parity with them which are <hi>inſufficient,</hi> you conclude the <hi>Letter</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> is not <hi>inſufficient. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Laws</hi> are of themſelves a <hi>ſufficient Rule,</hi> though lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to a <hi>miſ-interpretation,</hi> and ſo is <hi>Scripture.</hi> What need there is of <hi>publick Interpreters</hi> of either, <hi>who</hi> they are to be, or <hi>how</hi> qualified, is not now the <hi>Queſtion,</hi> nor ſhall you now engage me in it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Any body but your ſelf would have made another <hi>uſe</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:65387:18"/>of this <hi>Inſtance.</hi> As <hi>God</hi> can write much <hi>plainer</hi> than <hi>men,</hi> when he thinks fit, and has more care of their <hi>ſalvation,</hi> than they of their <hi>temporal concerns;</hi> another man would have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that <hi>God</hi> did <hi>not</hi> intend their <hi>ſalvation</hi> ſhould depend on the <hi>privately interpretable Letter</hi> of the <hi>Divine Law,</hi> which he left <hi>leſs plain</hi> than men made the <hi>Letter</hi> of <hi>humane Lows. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Another man poſſibly, with <hi>your ſelf</hi> at his Elbow to prompt him, might both <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> and <hi>conclude</hi> as <hi>miſely</hi> and <hi>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly</hi> too as you do: He might <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> firſt, that <hi>humane Laws</hi> are <hi>plainer</hi> than the <hi>divine Laws,</hi> which will not be granted him, and thence infer, that <hi>thoſe</hi> being of <hi>temperal concernment</hi> only, and <hi>theſe</hi> of <hi>eternal,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> being more careful of our <hi>ſalvation,</hi> than <hi>men</hi> of our <hi>temporal concerns,</hi> and able to ſpeak <hi>plainer</hi> than they, 'tis reaſonable to think, that <hi>God</hi> would give <hi>Laws leſs plain</hi> than theirs, leſt they ſhould be too <hi>eaſily underſtood,</hi> and men directed to <hi>ſalvation too plainly.</hi> For my part, I am too dull to learn this way of <hi>concluding,</hi> and muſt be content with this of my own. Becauſe <hi>God</hi> loves us, and hath the greateſt care of our <hi>ſalvation,</hi> and can ſpeak plain, he hath left us a <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>certain Rule.</hi> And becauſe I am ſure, and all <hi>Chriſtians</hi> agree that God hath left us his <hi>Laws</hi> in <hi>Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> and no where elſe that I can find, but in <hi>Scripture,</hi> he hath written them ſo <hi>plainly</hi> that we may <hi>underſtand</hi> them, and would have us take them for the <hi>certain Rule</hi> of <hi>Life.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>We are now free to paſs on to our <hi>Fourth Propoſition. Therefore Scripture's Letter interpretable by private Judgments, is not the Way left by God to know ſurely what Christ and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles taught, or ſurely to arrive at right Faith. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>This, when it was <hi>propoſed</hi> only to be proved, you call'd your <hi>Concluſion,</hi> and would not allow me to ſpeak to it. Now 'tis your <hi>concluſion,</hi> if there be any, (for of the <hi>Five Propoſitions</hi> whereof your Diſcourſe, as you ſay, conſiſted, this <hi>Fourth</hi> it ſhould ſeem is now the <hi>laſt</hi>) you call it only a <hi>Propoſition,</hi> and therefore I hope I have liberty to ſpeak to it.</p>
               <p>If then by <hi>Scripture's Letter</hi> you mean <hi>unſens'd Characters,</hi> I
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65387:19"/>confeſs it cannot be the <hi>Rule</hi> or <hi>Way</hi> to <hi>know.</hi> Yet if you can allow as much to <hi>Scripture</hi> as you would have us allow to <hi>your Letter,</hi> that it contains <hi>good ſence</hi> in <hi>words ſignificant</hi> and <hi>intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible,</hi> we deny your <hi>Propoſition.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I wiſh ſome body would tell me for you, whether you take <hi>Scripture's Letter,</hi> in this period, for <hi>unſenc'd</hi> or <hi>ſenc'd cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters;</hi> for truly I cannot tell my ſelf. <hi>R. p.</hi> 31.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>If you underſtand not <hi>Engliſh,</hi> I cannot help it; any body elſe might ſee I take it for <hi>ſenc'd characters.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>By the terms you put <hi>[intelligible]</hi> and <hi>[ſignificant]</hi> one would gueſs you mean <hi>unſenc'd characters.</hi> For <hi>[intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible]</hi> imports what may be underſtood, but <hi>is not</hi> yet; and <hi>[ſignificant]</hi> what <hi>may</hi> be perceived by the ſign, whether it <hi>be</hi> or <hi>no. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>You have a mind I ſee we ſhould know how excellent a <hi>Critick</hi> you are. You have now taught me what I confeſs I knew not before, that when a thing is <hi>underſtood,</hi> it is no longer <hi>intelligible,</hi> that is, <hi>cannot be underſtood;</hi> and that that is <hi>not ſignificant</hi> which doth <hi>ſignifie,</hi> but that is <hi>ſignificant</hi> which may be <hi>ſignified,</hi> whether it be perceived to be ſo or no. If it <hi>ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie,</hi> we muſt not call it <hi>ſignificant,</hi> or <hi>ſignifying;</hi> but if it be <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified,</hi> though it <hi>ſignifie nothing</hi> to us, we muſt call it <hi>ſignificant.</hi> Who ever heard ſuch ſtuff as this before from a <hi>Critick?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I ſhould remember you are of a <hi>Communion</hi> wherein ſuch <hi>Language</hi> may be as proper, as that other you mention (<hi>p.</hi> 1.2.) <hi>Worſhip</hi> in an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknown Tongue is no</hi> otherwiſe <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible,</hi> than as, <hi>That which may be underſtood, but is not yet.</hi> And <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> hath left no <hi>ſign</hi> to <hi>ſignifie,</hi> but makes the thing <hi>ſignified</hi> to be the thing <hi>ſignifying</hi> too, whether <hi>that which may be perceived by it, be ſo or no.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>ſence</hi> of the <hi>characters</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> is the <hi>ſence</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> and the <hi>ſence</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is that which we are to <hi>believe.</hi> And ſo <hi>Scripture-characters ſenced</hi> ſignifie <hi>Faith it ſelf</hi> in conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with thoſe <hi>characters. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>What means theſe words <hi>[in conjunction with thoſe chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters?]</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:65387:19"/>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>A <hi>character ſenc'd</hi> ſignifies a <hi>character</hi> with the <hi>ſence joyn'd</hi> to it. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>A <hi>character ſenc'd</hi> or <hi>unſenc'd,</hi> are expreſſions we were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver uſed to, but in reading ſuch. Writings as yours. You may therefore interpret your own Language as you pleaſe for me, whether we can underſtand you or no. For my part I can underſtand no more-by a <hi>ſenc'd character,</hi> but a <hi>character</hi> the <hi>ſignification</hi> whereof is <hi>intelligible.</hi> So <hi>Scripture-characters</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie <hi>Faith it ſelf,</hi> taken for the things to be believed, as is uſual.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faith</hi> is the <hi>end</hi> to which we are looking for a <hi>way</hi> to carry us. To tell us then that <hi>Scripture's Letter</hi> taken for <hi>ſenced Characters,</hi> is this <hi>Way,</hi> is to tell us the <hi>End</hi> is the <hi>Way</hi> to it ſelf; that the <hi>means</hi> to get <hi>Faith,</hi> is to <hi>have</hi> it firſt; that when we know it, we know it; — and ſuch fine things. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faith</hi> materially taken revealed in <hi>Scripture,</hi> is there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, that we may <hi>knew</hi> and <hi>believe</hi> it. To <hi>beget Faith</hi> in us, is the <hi>end</hi> of <hi>Faith's</hi> being there <hi>reveal'd.</hi> And ſo we ſay truly, that <hi>Faith ſignified</hi> in <hi>written characters</hi> is the <hi>way</hi> or <hi>means</hi> to beget <hi>Faith in us;</hi> or that the <hi>means</hi> to get <hi>Faith,</hi> is to ſeek it in the <hi>Scripture;</hi> that when we diſcern it <hi>there,</hi> we know what we are to <hi>believe.</hi> Theſe are plain things, which you by your fine <hi>Arts</hi> would make obſcure. Pray now keep your <hi>fine things</hi> for <hi>Bart'lemew Fair.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You are not a man to be diſcouraged with ill ſucceſs. You are at your <hi>diſtinctions</hi> again. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Much, I fear, againſt your will, who ſeem to delight in <hi>confuſion.</hi> If again by theſe words <hi>[interpretable by private Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments]</hi> you mean, <hi>any way interpretable,</hi> as any <hi>private</hi> man may poſſibly <hi>wreſt</hi> the words to make them comply with his own <hi>Sentiments,</hi> or through <hi>ignorance, lazineſs,</hi> and <hi>neglect</hi> of <hi>helps</hi> and <hi>means</hi> fit to be uſed, may <hi>miſ-underſtand</hi> them; you muſt have as wide a <hi>Conſcience</hi> and as little <hi>Modeſty,</hi> as the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent and wicked <hi>Author</hi> of <hi>PAX VOBIS,</hi> who has the face to faſten ſuch a meaning on the ſixth of our 39 <hi>Articles,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65387:20"/>But if you mean, that <hi>Scripture</hi> as it may be <hi>underſtood</hi> by a <hi>private</hi> man of a <hi>competent Judgment,</hi> uſing ſuch <hi>helps</hi> as are proper, is not the <hi>Way,</hi> we again deny your <hi>aſſumption,</hi> or if you will, your <hi>Fourth Propoſition. A. p.</hi> 13, 14.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I will, by your good leave, ſay in ſhort, <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Bad Judgments, R. p.</hi> 32.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>As you pleaſe, Sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I take you then to ſay, that <hi>Scripture's Letter,</hi> as <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretable by bad Judgments, is not the way;</hi> but as <hi>interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by good Judgments, is the way. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>You <hi>miſtake</hi> me then: for I ſay it is not the <hi>Way</hi> as <hi>any way interpretable,</hi> or as it may be <hi>wreſted</hi> either by <hi>good</hi> or <hi>bad Judgments.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>By this account <hi>three</hi> parts in <hi>four</hi> of Mankind at a modeſt computation, have <hi>no Way:</hi> for ſo many <hi>bad Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> there are at leaſt. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Not very <hi>modeſt,</hi> to conclude ſo haſtily, that <hi>three</hi> parts in <hi>four</hi> cannot <hi>underſtand,</hi> with all the <hi>helps</hi> God affords them, the <hi>Scripture</hi> in their <hi>own</hi> Language.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>While we are inquiring which is the <hi>Way</hi> which God hath left, pray what have we to do with the <hi>Judgments of men?</hi> Can they make or unmake it? <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Why are you then ſo buſie with that, wherewith you have nothing to do? Why, whether we will or no, and when we forbid you to do it, will you, when you talk of the Way which God hath left, meddle with <hi>private Judgments?</hi> Are not thoſe the <hi>Judgments</hi> of <hi>men?</hi> Were you not in a <hi>Dreams</hi> and fancy'd that <hi>we</hi> ſaid what no body but <hi>your ſelf</hi> ſaid?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Your <hi>diſtinction</hi> unluckily has no relation at all to the <hi>Queſtion. R. p.</hi> 33.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Moſt <hi>unluckily</hi> indeed to <hi>you,</hi> it has ſo near a relation to your <hi>Propoſition,</hi> that it ſhews, now you have made it your <hi>concluſion,</hi> that you <hi>conclude</hi> nothing to the <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay, that <hi>bad Judgments</hi> may <hi>miſ underſtand</hi> the <hi>Letter</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> and that it is <hi>not</hi> the <hi>way</hi> to ſuch; which
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:65387:20"/>I think, is to ſay, that becauſe they may <hi>miſunderſtand</hi> it, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is <hi>not</hi> the <hi>Way. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Where ſaid I, it is not the <hi>Way</hi> to ſuch? Beware of <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionable falſifying;</hi> and then be at what pains you will to tell us that you have read <hi>Bayes</hi> his <hi>Play,</hi> and learn'd of him to talk like a <hi>Player. Pag.</hi> 34.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Queſtion</hi> is, Whether <hi>Scripture's Letter interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table by Private Judgments</hi> be the <hi>Way</hi> left by God. <hi>R. p.</hi> 35.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Is it ſo? Anſwer then your own <hi>Queſtion,</hi> while we are enquiring after the <hi>Way</hi> left by God, what have we to do with <hi>Private Judgments?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I maintain it is not; and prove it, becauſe men, who take that <hi>way, err. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>What you maintain in oppoſition to us, pray ſee it be <hi>oppoſite</hi> to our <hi>Doctrine.</hi> As to your <hi>proof,</hi> it needs another <hi>proof</hi> yet, <hi>viz.</hi> That men who take the <hi>right way,</hi> may not <hi>err</hi> from it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I thought it needed no proving, that the <hi>Way</hi> leſt by <hi>God</hi> is not the <hi>Way</hi> to <hi>Error. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>But this doth, that men who <hi>take</hi> it, may-<hi>not err</hi> from it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Propoſition</hi> is of the <hi>Letter Interpretable,</hi> that is, <hi>not yet interpreted,</hi> or which has not the <hi>ſence put to it,</hi> and ſo is yet <hi>unſenſed. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Then your <hi>Propoſition</hi> is of <hi>ſenſleſs Characters,</hi> that they are not the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> which being <hi>granted</hi> you, you op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe no body, and ſo are left to diſpute with your ſelf.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>When you diſtinguiſh the <hi>Letter Interpretable</hi> into <hi>ſenſed</hi> and <hi>unſenſed,</hi> you make a <hi>diſtinction,</hi> whereof one branch is not comprehended in the <hi>Notion</hi> to be <hi>divided. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis your <hi>own diſtinction</hi> indeed, Sir, and was never mine. You know I told you, (<hi>A. p.</hi> 13.) <hi>that we are unacquainted with ſuch infignificant things as unſens'd Characters in Scripture;</hi> how then ſhould I diſtinguiſh the <hi>Letter</hi> into <hi>ſenſed</hi> and <hi>unſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> I only asked you which branch of your own <hi>ſenſeleſs diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> you meant. You now tell me, you meant <hi>unſenſeable cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters,</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:65387:21"/>and that the <hi>Letter Interpretable</hi> can be no other: If ſo, for my part I think 'tis <hi>nothing,</hi> for I cannot ſee how <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſed Characters</hi> are <hi>Interpretable</hi> at all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Your <hi>ſecond Diſtinction</hi> is of <hi>Judgments</hi> into <hi>competent</hi> and <hi>incompetent,</hi> which is Twin to the former. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Are all <hi>competent</hi> then, or all <hi>incompetent,</hi> or are they <hi>neither?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I vouch'd for proof <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi> men of very <hi>competent judgments,</hi> who fall under none of your <hi>ill qualifications. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Then may they underſtand the <hi>Scripture</hi> in Points of <hi>Faith;</hi> or if they may not, they are of <hi>incompetent judgments.</hi> You ſuppoſe them to err, and yet to fall under none of my <hi>ill qualifications</hi> of <hi>Ignorance, Lazineſs,</hi> or <hi>Negligence.</hi> But how can you <hi>prove</hi> they do not? However, there is yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind an <hi>ill qualification</hi> mentioned there by me, that you take no notice of: Why then may they not be of thoſe who <hi>wreſt Scripture to comply with their own Sentiments,</hi> ſuch as I told you (<hi>A. p.</hi> 15.) you might find enow of nearer home? This humour, I now tell you, I take to be the ſourſe of the moſt pernicious <hi>Miſinterpretations,</hi> as I fear it may be amongſt <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians;</hi> and alſo ſome others, who affecting a <hi>Supremacy,</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſo long to find it in <hi>Scripture,</hi> till at laſt they think they have found it in every <hi>Verſe</hi> that ſpeaks well of St. <hi>Peter:</hi> in like manner as they will needs prove <hi>Tradition</hi> it ſelf, thô the foundation of all <hi>certainty,</hi> by <hi>Scripture,</hi> our derided <hi>Rule.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I foretold I ſhould have nothing but an <hi>unconcerning return</hi> for an <hi>anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Either my <hi>Anſwer</hi> is a <hi>concerning return</hi> to your <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> or your <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> is not <hi>concerning</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainty</hi> of our <hi>Faith,</hi> much leſs hath it ſhewn the <hi>Nullity</hi> of our <hi>Rule,</hi> which you ſay it <hi>undertook</hi> to do. And truly I might have <hi>foretold,</hi> as eaſily as you, that it was in vain to expect from him, who had <hi>proclaim'd</hi> his Diſcourſe <hi>unanſwerable</hi> any <hi>acknowledgment</hi> that it <hi>was anſwer'd.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:65387:21"/>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You conclude with an <hi>Argument</hi> againſt my <hi>Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. R. p.</hi> 36.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>No <hi>Argument</hi> by your favour, Sir, nor did I <hi>conclude</hi> my <hi>Anſwer</hi> with it, as you well know. I was but telling in what ſence your <hi>Propoſition</hi> (after which <hi>two</hi> more then follow'd, thô but <hi>one</hi> of them now appear) muſt be taken, if you would prove any thing againſt us. To this purpoſe, I laid before you ſeveral <hi>Suppoſitions</hi> of ours, which you muſt by your <hi>proof</hi> overthrow, if you proved any thing to purpoſe. This is it you now call a <hi>concluding</hi> with an <hi>Argument</hi> againſt your <hi>concluſion.</hi> And laugh at your own conceit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> then—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, we ſuppoſe, 1. <hi>That the Scripture is God's Word. A. p.</hi> 14.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>So do I too provided you mean the <hi>true ſence</hi> of it. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>We mean no other. 2. <hi>That it was written to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Undoubtedly, but not by every one, barely by means of the <hi>Letter — Books</hi> without <hi>Maſters</hi> will make but few <hi>Grammarians</hi> or <hi>Mathematicians. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>And ſuch <hi>Maſters</hi> we want not. 3. <hi>That it is written for the Inſtruction of Private Men.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, but not the <hi>only</hi> or <hi>ſufficient means</hi> of their <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> barely by the <hi>Letter. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Not, ſuppoſing that <hi>Letter</hi> an <hi>unſenſed Character:</hi> nor, taking it as <hi>ſens'd,</hi> (as we always do) is it ſo our <hi>Rule</hi> or <hi>Means</hi> as to exclude all <hi>other Means</hi> for the underſtanding it. 4. <hi>That Private Men are concern'd to underſtand it.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, and as much concern'd not to <hi>miſunderſtand it. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis true. 5. <hi>That they have Means left them of God for the underſtanding of it, ſo far as it is of neceſſary concernment to them.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, and that <hi>abſolutely certain Means,</hi> the <hi>Publick Interpretation</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> or <hi>Tradition.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Means</hi> ſo ſufficient, as they need not fear but by the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:65387:22"/>
                  <hi>bleſſing of God</hi> on their pious endeavours to underſtand it; among which is the <hi>Publick Interpretation</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>written Tradition</hi> in the <hi>Creeds</hi> and <hi>Firſt Councils.</hi> 6. <hi>That uſing theſe Means as they ought, they may underſtand it, and thus it is to them the way to know ſurely what Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught as neceſſary to their ſalvation.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Never mince it with <hi>May;</hi> they <hi>ſhall</hi> and <hi>certainly ſhall</hi> underſtand it who <hi>uſe</hi> the Means. <hi>R. p.</hi> 37.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Not unleſs they uſe them as they <hi>ought,</hi> ſo indeed they <hi>certainly ſhall.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>'Twas ill forgot, when your hand was in at <hi>ſuppoſing,</hi> not to <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> in among the reſt, that <hi>Private Interpretation</hi> is the Means left by God for underſtanding <hi>Scripture. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I left that for you, Sir, to <hi>ſuppoſe,</hi> leſt having no Doctrine of ours to oppoſe, you ſhould for want of a <hi>ſuppoſition</hi> of your own, have nothing at all to do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>If <hi>Publick Interpretation</hi> be thoſe Means, as it needs muſt, ſince I have proved, that <hi>Private</hi> is not; the <hi>Scripture</hi> plainly is no <hi>way</hi> to thoſe who only rely on the <hi>Private</hi> Means to underſtand it. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>You have prov'd you ſay, that <hi>Private Interpretation</hi> is not the <hi>Means</hi> of underſtanding <hi>Scripture;</hi> whilſt the thing you <hi>undertook</hi> to prove was the <hi>Nullity</hi> of our <hi>Rule,</hi> the <hi>Scripture</hi> itſelf. You ſuppoſe elſewhere <hi>Private Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to be our <hi>Rule,</hi> and now you would have me to ſuppoſe it is the <hi>Means</hi> of Underſtanding our <hi>Rule;</hi> and will needs ſay you have proved it is not, and thence Infer, that <hi>Publick Interpretation</hi> is the <hi>Means:</hi> pray, Sir, for <hi>Logick's</hi> ſake, tell me, if this be a <hi>good conſequence,</hi> without the help of another <hi>ſuppoſition,</hi> that there is no <hi>other means,</hi> which is yet unproved. Yet grant you this, <hi>Scripture</hi> ſtill Remains the <hi>Way</hi> or <hi>Rule,</hi> even to thoſe who rely only on <hi>Private Interpretation,</hi> this only follows from your <hi>Premiſes,</hi> that they uſe not the <hi>right Means</hi> of Underſtanding it. To tell you now my thoughts, <hi>Interpretation</hi> is not ſo properly call'd the <hi>Means,</hi> as the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of the <hi>Means.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:65387:22"/>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Your <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are much beholding to your <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which ſhews, that <hi>Scripture Interpreted,</hi> as <hi>they Interpret</hi> it, by <hi>Private Judgments,</hi> is no <hi>Way</hi> to them. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>My telling you what <hi>Proteſtants</hi> hold, will ſhew no ſuch thing as you imagine; but let you alone to ſhew your <hi>Art</hi> in turning it into an <hi>Argument,</hi> and then they will ſoon ſee how much they are obliged to ſomebody.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Had you been confident of your performance againſt my <hi>Argument,</hi> you would never have thought of <hi>changing</hi> it, as you do, <hi>page</hi> 17. <hi>R. p.</hi> 18.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I muſt not contend with you in <hi>confidence</hi> of our own Performances, yet am I ſtill ſo confident that your <hi>Argument</hi> has proved nothing to the purpoſe, that I dare tell you again, that if you will <hi>prove</hi> what you <hi>undertook</hi> to <hi>ſhew,</hi> (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I think you meant <hi>proving</hi>) you muſt thus frame your Argument. <hi>God hath left us ſome Way or Rule, which no man can poſſibly miſunderſtand or abuſe; The Scripture-Letter is not ſuch a Way or Rule as no man can poſſibly miſunderſtand or abuſe; Therefore, The Scripture-Letter is not the Way or Rule which God hath left us.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>No body elſe would have left out the <hi>Principal Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſing the Rule,</hi> and ſo coming to the right <hi>Faith</hi> by <hi>uſing</hi> it. <hi>R. p.</hi> 38.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Put in thoſe words then, when you pleaſe, thô I think them not very needful, ſeeing <hi>Miſunderſtanding</hi> and <hi>Abuſing</hi> ſeem to me ſufficiently to imply an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſing</hi> of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Your <hi>Argument</hi> has all the Faults of your <hi>Anſwer,</hi> in ſhort.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Be it ſo, and farewel to it; for if it may not be ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to <hi>you,</hi> it is I am ſure of no uſe at all to <hi>me.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="dialogue">
            <head>The Third Dialogue.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>TO prove the <hi>Infallibility</hi> of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> (or as you put it, the <hi>Abſolute Certainty</hi> of the <hi>Catholick
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:65387:23"/>Rule</hi>) You will grant to be your part, if you think it <hi>need</hi> any proof, as I queſtion whether you do or no, for (<hi>L. p.</hi> 12.) you ſay, <hi>It is vain to talk against one</hi> Infallibility, <hi>unleſs we will ſet up another.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>It has been demonſtrated to you, (<hi>Faith Vindic. p.</hi> 37, 38.) that <hi>Infallibility</hi> and <hi>Certainty</hi> are the ſame. <hi>R. p.</hi> 39.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I have not ſeen your <hi>Demonſtrations</hi> yet, nor can I hope that I ever ſhall; becauſe I am ſure there are <hi>degrees</hi> of <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty,</hi> and there can be none of <hi>Infallibility.</hi> If you think otherwiſe, to what purpoſe talk you of <hi>Abſolute Certainty,</hi> and will not conſent to have the word left out. If <hi>Certainty</hi> be no <hi>leſs</hi> than <hi>Infallibility, Abſolute Certainty</hi> can be no <hi>more,</hi> therefore you might have ſpared the word.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nature</hi> tells us, that all <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> ſuppoſes ſomething <hi>Certain. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>What thon?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>How is it poſſible then to <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> againſt <hi>Infallibility,</hi> or any thing elſe, without ſetting up and proceeding upon ſomething that is <hi>Certain,</hi> or <hi>Infallibly</hi> true? <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>A <hi>Certainty</hi> we grant, <hi>Infallibility</hi> we deny. The <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer's</hi> enough to ground a rational <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> upon, even againſt <hi>Infallibility.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>If you will needs declare againſt <hi>Infallible Certainty;</hi> be but ſo candid, as to ſay ſtill you are <hi>Fallibly Certain,</hi> and ſee how your <hi>Readers</hi> will ſmile at your <hi>Folly.</hi> Pray ſpeak to this Point. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>To be ſtill telling men, what they know already, might make them <hi>ſmile</hi> indeed; but ſhould we tell them, whilſt we are denying <hi>Infallibility,</hi> that we are <hi>infallible,</hi> it would make them <hi>laugh</hi> outright.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Are you not <hi>deſerters</hi> of <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> ſuppoſing there is no <hi>Infallibility,</hi> that is, <hi>true Certainty</hi> to be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men? <hi>R p.</hi> 40.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>True Certainty</hi> there is, and that's enough for <hi>Human Nature.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:65387:23"/>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Are you not <hi>heirayers</hi> of <hi>Chriſtion Faith,</hi> whilſt you leave it all capable to be a <hi>lye;</hi> nay, maintain the full ſence of that wicked Poſition, <hi>[All Chriſtian Faith is paſſible to be falſe]</hi> in Diſcourſes directly framed for that for purpoſe? <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Have the <hi>Authors</hi> of thoſe <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> no Names? Or are you <hi>too modest</hi> to name them? All we ſay, is, That <hi>Men</hi> are capable of being <hi>deceived.</hi> We affirm ourſelves as <hi>certain</hi> as <hi>men</hi> can be, that no part of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith</hi> can be a <hi>lye,</hi> or is <hi>poſſible</hi> to be <hi>falſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Are you not <hi>Blaſphemers</hi> of <hi>God's Providence,</hi> in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring that he hath left leſs <hi>certain</hi> grounds for <hi>Faith,</hi> and for the <hi>ſalvation</hi> of <hi>Mankind,</hi> for which the <hi>World</hi> was <hi>created,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> himſelf <hi>died,</hi> than he hath for other things of <hi>trifling</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Do we <hi>declare</hi> all this, when we ſay, <hi>The</hi> Infallible God <hi>hath by Men</hi> inſpired <hi>with his</hi> Infallible Spirit, <hi>left us his</hi> Word plainly written, <hi>which is a ſufficient means to ſecure us from being</hi> dangerouſly deceived <hi>in any thing neceſſary to our</hi> Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>if we diligently attend unto it, and uſe the proper helps of underſtanding it? A. p.</hi> 17, 18.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Will it <hi>expiate</hi> from thoſe <hi>Crimes,</hi> to talk <hi>cantingly?</hi> —Sayings fit to take the good Women that are much pleas'd with <hi>Godly talk</hi> in a <hi>Sermon,</hi> but <hi>frivalous</hi> in our <hi>Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie! Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, <hi>Sayings,</hi> that ſhew his <hi>wickedneſs,</hi> that focuſeth us for denying the <hi>certainty</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> againſt his own knowledge; and eſteems the <hi>talking</hi> of what <hi>God</hi> hath done to ſecure us from <hi>Error, frivolous Talk</hi> in a <hi>controverſie</hi> about the Certainty of our <hi>Faith;</hi> and which ſhow we have <hi>ſufficient certainty.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I ſuppoſe you mean a <hi>certainty</hi> that is neither <hi>fallible</hi> nor <hi>infallible. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>An <hi>undoubted certainty,</hi> ſo as we <hi>cannot doubt</hi> that we are, thô 'tis not <hi>impoſſible</hi> but we may be <hi>deceiv'd.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You tell men, that after all their pains, they can never
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:65387:24"/>be <hi>ſatisfied,</hi> but their <hi>Faith</hi> may be <hi>falſe,</hi> that is, they can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be <hi>ſatisfied</hi> that it is <hi>true. R. p.</hi> 41.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Not <hi>ſatisfied?</hi> Yes, <hi>fully.</hi> Which they can never be, if they muſt ſtay till they be <hi>infallible.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>When the <hi>certainty</hi> of your Grounds fail you, your laſt <hi>Refuge</hi> is, that the ſame <hi>Infallible God,</hi> that hath given the <hi>means,</hi> has aſſured his <hi>bleſſing</hi> to them that diligently uſe them. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I confeſs, 'tis <hi>God's bleſſing</hi> we moſt truſt to. And if you can hope for <hi>certainty</hi> by the uſe of any <hi>means</hi> without it, 'tis more than we can do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>This begs the <hi>Queſtion:</hi> For if the <hi>Rule</hi> you follow be not the <hi>means</hi> ordain'd by <hi>God</hi> to arrive at <hi>Faith,</hi> you have neither the <hi>right means,</hi> nor can you be aſſured of any <hi>bleſſing</hi> by uſing them. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>The preſent <hi>Queſtion</hi> is of <hi>Infallibility,</hi> without which, ſay you, we want <hi>means</hi> of ſecuring us from being <hi>deceived,</hi> and are diſcouraged from taking due <hi>pains</hi> to compaſs the good we deſire. No, ſay I, for thô there be no <hi>Infallibility</hi> among men, yet if we uſe the <hi>means,</hi> we may be ſecured by the promiſe of a <hi>bleſſing</hi> from the <hi>infallible God.</hi> How doth this beg the <hi>Queſtion?</hi> If our <hi>Certainty</hi> be not enough, where ſhall we find this <hi>Infallibility</hi> of your's? In <hi>Tradition</hi> ſure, if any where; for after we have been ſent from place to place to ſeek it, we have miſſed it every where elſe. <hi>A. p.</hi> 18.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Pray, Sir, who <hi>ſent</hi> you? <hi>We</hi> with whom you are diſcourſing, never directed you to any other, but to that of <hi>Tradition. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> they were who ſent us. And who <hi>you</hi> are, I know not, whether <hi>One</hi> or <hi>Many,</hi> or what your <hi>We</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>What an everlaſting Trifler are you, to confeſs you have been running after <hi>Butterfties</hi> all this while? <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Is your <hi>Infallibility</hi> but a <hi>Butterfly.</hi> Then it is fitter for <hi>you</hi> to keep and <hi>play</hi> with, than for <hi>me</hi> to <hi>run after.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:65387:24"/>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>certainty</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> is from <hi>Tradition. L. p.</hi> 7.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>We have the <hi>Books</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> from <hi>Tradition,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ap.</hi> 19.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Therefore <hi>Tradition</hi> cauſes <hi>certainty. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tradition</hi> we own a ground of <hi>ſufficient certainty</hi> of this matter of <hi>Fact</hi> — But this <hi>Tradition</hi> is not <hi>that</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> only, but a more <hi>univerſal Tradition</hi> of <hi>all Chriſtians. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Then <hi>Tradition</hi> makes <hi>Faith</hi> as <hi>certain</hi> as <hi>Scripture. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Conveying the <hi>Book</hi> to us, it conveys the <hi>Faith</hi> contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>Book;</hi> and witneſſing to the <hi>Book,</hi> as written by men <hi>divinely inſpired;</hi> it gives as good credit to the <hi>Faith</hi> therein contain'd, as <hi>humane Teſtimony</hi> can do, yet this <hi>certainty</hi> comes not up to <hi>Infallibility. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, it does: for the <hi>certainty</hi> here ſpoken of, was <hi>abſolute certainty;</hi> and I proved it was the ſame with <hi>Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility. R. p.</hi> 42.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It does ſo, I know in <hi>your</hi> Account. But I now ſay, <hi>humane Teſtimony</hi> is not enough to ground an <hi>infallible certainty</hi> upon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay, <hi>Tradition</hi> for <hi>Scripture</hi> was more <hi>univerſal;</hi> ſuppoſe it ſo, was not <hi>Tradition</hi> for <hi>Doctrine</hi> large enough to cauſe <hi>abſolute certainty? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>More univerſal,</hi> I meant and ſaid, than <hi>that</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> only, yet not enough to cauſe <hi>abſolute,</hi> that is with you, <hi>infallible certainty.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Are not <hi>Ten-Millions</hi> of <hi>Atteſters</hi> as able to cauſe <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute certainty,</hi> as <hi>Twenty? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caeteris paribus,</hi> the <hi>more Atteſters,</hi> the <hi>more certainty;</hi> yet how many ſoever, they are but <hi>men,</hi> and <hi>fallible.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>When the number comes to that <hi>pitch,</hi> that it is <hi>ſeen</hi> to be <hi>impoſſible</hi> they ſhould all be <hi>deceived</hi> in the thing they u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimouſly <hi>attest,</hi> or conſpire to <hi>deceive</hi> us; their <hi>Teſtimony</hi> has its full effect upon us, and begets in us that <hi>firm</hi> and <hi>unal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable aſſent</hi> we call <hi>abſolute certainty:</hi> and the addition of <hi>Myriads</hi> more, adds nothing to the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of that <hi>Aſſent,</hi> ſince 'tis wrought without it. <hi>R. p.</hi> 43.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>This is as good <hi>aſſurance</hi> of a matter of <hi>Fact,</hi> as any man
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:65387:25"/>can deſire; but what's all this to <hi>Infallibility?</hi> Here's ſome certain <hi>pitch</hi> of number <hi>(which is it, I wiſh you could ſhew us)</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which when <hi>Atteſters</hi> (<hi>every man of them</hi> fallible) are come, (<hi>one</hi> unite <hi>ſhort may ſpoil all</hi>) it may be <hi>ſeen</hi> (infallibly <hi>or we may be deceived</hi>) that 'tis <hi>impoſſible</hi> (<hi>no</hi> leſs <hi>will ſerve</hi>) they ſhould be <hi>deceived</hi> or <hi>deceive.</hi> Thus add <hi>fallible</hi> to <hi>fallible,</hi> they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>infallible,</hi> and <hi>infallibly honest</hi> too. And then we may <hi>firmly aſſent</hi> (<hi>it ſhould have been</hi> infallibly) and the addition of <hi>Myriads</hi> more, will adde nothing to the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of that <hi>aſſent,</hi> ſince it is wrought without it. Now what this <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> is but <hi>aſſent,</hi> who knows? Of the <hi>firmneſs</hi> of <hi>aſſent,</hi> I am ſure there are <hi>degrees.</hi> Do not theſe words ſeem then to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, that though <hi>Myriads</hi> of <hi>Atteſters</hi> cannot add to <hi>aſſent,</hi> barely conſider'd as ſuch, for ſo it was before; yet poſſibly they may add to the <hi>degrees</hi> of <hi>firmneſs?</hi> If ſo, then ſeeing that <hi>aſſent</hi> was before <hi>infallible,</hi> do not you ſeem to admit <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees</hi> of <hi>Infallibility?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>But the main is, you quite miſtake the nature of a long <hi>ſucceſſive Teſtimony. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>My comfort is, I have a wiſe and <hi>compaſſionate Inſtructer</hi> to ſet me right.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Let <hi>Ten Thouſand</hi> men witneſs what <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three,</hi> who were the <hi>original Atteſters</hi> of a thing ſaid at firſt; and <hi>Twenty Thouſand</hi> more witneſs in the next Age what thoſe <hi>Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand</hi> told them, and ſo forwards, yet (taking them <hi>preciſely</hi> as <hi>Witneſſes</hi>) they amount to no more, in order to <hi>prove</hi> the <hi>truth</hi> of that thing, than the <hi>credit</hi> of thoſe <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three</hi> firſt <hi>Witneſſes</hi> goes. <hi>R. p.</hi> 43.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>All this I knew before. Where's my <hi>miſtake</hi> all this while?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Tradition</hi> for the ſeveral <hi>Books</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> is not in any degree comparable either in regard of the <hi>largeneſs</hi> or the <hi>firmneſs</hi> of the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> to the <hi>Tradition</hi> for <hi>Doctrine. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I <hi>grant</hi> not this, yet let's <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> it in part at preſent. I ſee <hi>firſt,</hi> that your charging me with <hi>miſtaking</hi> the nature of a <hi>ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Teſtimony</hi> aroſe from a <hi>miſtake</hi> of your own. I ſaid we
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:65387:25"/>have a <hi>larger Teſtimony</hi> for <hi>Scripture</hi> than <hi>that</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> you fancy me to ſpeak of a <hi>larger Teſtimony</hi> for <hi>Scripture</hi> than for <hi>Doctrine.</hi> And ſo all you have ſaid ſince, is to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Again, though the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> were <hi>larger</hi> for <hi>Doctrine</hi> than for <hi>Scripture,</hi> yet is it not ſo <hi>firm,</hi> becauſe not ſo <hi>competent</hi> an <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſter</hi> of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> as of a <hi>Book.</hi> It is <hi>ſufficient</hi> indeed for the <hi>Book,</hi> the <hi>Doctrine</hi> whereof depends on the <hi>credit</hi> of the <hi>first Atteſters,</hi> and being <hi>ſufficiently atteſted</hi> by them, leaves no <hi>credit</hi> for any <hi>other Doctrine</hi> not agreeing with it, by how many ſoever at this day <hi>atteſted.</hi> Still yours is but <hi>humane Teſtimony,</hi> and that's not <hi>infallible.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Is not your <hi>Tradition</hi> for <hi>Scripture, humane too? R p.</hi> 44.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>If that may be <hi>erroneous,</hi> may not all <hi>Chriſtian Faith</hi> be a company of <hi>lying Stories? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>We have no reaſon to <hi>think</hi> or <hi>doubt</hi> it <hi>is,</hi> and therefore ought not to <hi>ſay</hi> it <hi>may be.</hi> I told you before, that neither <hi>Papiſts</hi> nor <hi>Proteſtants</hi> content themſelves with <hi>Tradition</hi> for the <hi>truth</hi> of their <hi>Faith,</hi> but produce abundance of other <hi>Arguments</hi> for it. <hi>A. p:</hi> 19. But you had no end to trace me there.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Seeing <hi>certainty</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> is proved by <hi>Tradition,</hi> what ſhould hinder me from <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> that unleſs ſome <hi>ſpecial difficulty</hi> be found in <hi>other things</hi> that light into the ſame cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, it muſt bring them down <hi>infallibly</hi> too? <hi>R. p.</hi> 45.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>If no <hi>ſpecial difficulty</hi> be found in them, you may <hi>infer</hi> it may bring them down as <hi>certainly.</hi> Theſe <hi>other things</hi> are, I ſuppoſe, things <hi>unwritten</hi> in that holy <hi>Book.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>So your <hi>gift</hi> of <hi>interpretation</hi> expounds theſe words of mine, but I do aſſure you, Sir, you are mightily <hi>miſtaken. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>All things <hi>written</hi> in the <hi>Book</hi> are convey'd down in it, what then can thoſe <hi>other things</hi> be, but things <hi>unwritten</hi> in it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I never yet told you that <hi>all Faith</hi> was not contain'd in <hi>Scripture explicitly</hi> or <hi>implicitly. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Well, if <hi>all</hi> be either <hi>explicitly</hi> or <hi>implicitly</hi> in the <hi>Book,</hi> then by <hi>Tradition all</hi> is brought down in the <hi>Book</hi> ſtill <hi>impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citly</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:65387:26"/>at leaſt. And then once more, whan can thoſe <hi>other things</hi> be, but things <hi>not written</hi> in <hi>Scripture?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>whole Body</hi> of <hi>Chriſt's Doctrine,</hi> nay the <hi>ſelf-ſame Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> that is contain'd in <hi>Scripture,</hi> comes down by <hi>Tradition</hi> or the <hi>Church's Teſtimony. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I had told you all this, but ſtill you talk'd of <hi>other things.</hi> How, I beſeech you, <hi>other things,</hi> and yet <hi>the ſame?</hi> What mean you by <hi>[nay the ſame?]</hi> A man would think by this you made the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> either but a <hi>part,</hi> or not ſo <hi>much</hi> as a part of the <hi>whole Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>But with this <hi>difference</hi> (as to the <hi>manner</hi>) among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that the <hi>Church</hi> that <hi>teſtifies</hi> it, having the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of it in her <hi>breaſt,</hi> can <hi>explain</hi> her meaning ſo, as to put it out of all <hi>queſtion</hi> to <hi>Learners, Doubters,</hi> and <hi>Inquirers,</hi> which the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> cannot. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Here's a <hi>difference</hi> indeed! The <hi>Doctrine</hi> is contain'd in <hi>Scripture,</hi> but it cannot <hi>diſcover</hi> it ſelf there to <hi>Learners,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>ſame</hi> is in the <hi>Church's breast,</hi> and there alone it may be <hi>learn'd.</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> teſtifies of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> that it is the <hi>Word of God,</hi> but 'tis <hi>Jeſuitically</hi> with an <hi>Aequivocation</hi> or <hi>Mental Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation,</hi> for it is not indeed the <hi>Word of God,</hi> but a <hi>dead Letter</hi> till the <hi>ſenſe</hi> be <hi>put</hi> to it, and that's in <hi>her breast.</hi> We have now found the <hi>Scrinium pectoris,</hi> but what's in the <hi>Box,</hi> who knows, or when it will all come forth? However, the <hi>whole ſenſe</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> is ſafely <hi>lock'd</hi> up there, and by the <hi>Key</hi> of <hi>Oral Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> it may be open'd as there is occaſion. Now to me it ſeems all one, whether theſe (call them <hi>ſame</hi> or <hi>other</hi> things) be <hi>contain'd</hi> or <hi>not contain'd,</hi> be <hi>explicitly</hi> or <hi>implicitly</hi> in <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture;</hi> they are <hi>there,</hi> if they be <hi>there</hi> at all, to no purpoſe, whilſt the <hi>ſenſe</hi> is in her <hi>breast.</hi> Not a ruſh matter if ſuch a <hi>Book</hi> had ſunk in the <hi>chanel.</hi> Yet it ſeems the <hi>Church</hi> had the kindneſs to hold up the <hi>empty Cabinet</hi> in her hand, whilſt ſhe ſecured the <hi>Jewel</hi> in her <hi>boſom.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s <hi>Ship</hi> (the <hi>Church</hi>) that caught ſo many <hi>Fiſhes</hi> at firſt, (the Body of <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi>—) hath ſtored up
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:65387:26"/>Proviſion enough for the ſucceſſion of <hi>Faith</hi> to the Worlds end, and there we may find it to our hands. We need not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>fiſh</hi> for our <hi>Faith</hi> in the <hi>chanel</hi> of <hi>Tyber,</hi> as your great Wit tells us. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I would not though for two pence, not have ventur'd that little <hi>Conceit</hi> of mine, ſeeing it is return'd home again with ſo rare a <hi>diſcovery.</hi> It would not be <hi>mannerly</hi> to enquire, when <hi>Ships</hi> catch <hi>Fiſhes,</hi> when they <hi>ſail,</hi> or when they <hi>ſink;</hi> nor how <hi>Fiſhes</hi> catch <hi>themſelves,</hi> or how the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> which are the <hi>Church,</hi> are caught by the <hi>Church</hi> which is that <hi>Body;</hi> or how thoſe <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are now the <hi>Proviſion</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> ſtored up to the World's end? 'Tis plain, you mean the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> hath the <hi>whole Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> ſtored up in her <hi>breast</hi> for all Ages, and we are fools for ſeeking it in the <hi>unſenſed cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> where 'tis not. Yet have <hi>you,</hi> Sir, a <hi>worthy opinion</hi> of the <hi>Scripture.</hi> I would have ſaid, St. <hi>Peter</hi> and his <hi>Partners</hi> with their <hi>Net,</hi> the <hi>Word of God,</hi> caught <hi>Men</hi> inſtead of <hi>Fiſhes,</hi> as <hi>Christ</hi> had promiſed; and with the ſame <hi>Net</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey'd to us by <hi>Tradition</hi> in <hi>Scripture,</hi> the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> do ſtill <hi>fiſh</hi> with good ſucceſs. Conſider if this <hi>Allegorizing</hi> of yours, would not ſuit better alſo with one of your <hi>Sermons,</hi> than with your <hi>Controverſie.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>All this is but <hi>prelude.</hi> Now comes Mr. <hi>G.</hi>'s <hi>Argument,</hi> the <hi>first Propoſition</hi> whereof is this: <hi>All Traditionary Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans believe the ſame to day, which they did yeſterday, and ſo up to the time of our Bleſſed Saviour.</hi> There is no denying this <hi>Propoſition,</hi> but by affirming, that <hi>Traditionary Chriſtians</hi> are not <hi>Traditionary Chriſtians. L. p.</hi> 8.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>But ſuppoſe theſe <hi>Traditionary Chriſtians</hi> be ſo call'd from their adhering to a <hi>Tradition</hi> which reacheth not ſo high as our <hi>B. Saviour</hi>'s time, but only <hi>pertends</hi> to it, <hi>&amp;c. A. p.</hi> 20.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Whether we only <hi>pretend</hi> to it or no, will be ſeen, when the <hi>Fourth Propoſition</hi> comes to be examined. <hi>R. p.</hi> 26. The <hi>Second Propoſition</hi> is this: <hi>If they follow this</hi> Rule, <hi>they cannot err in</hi> Faith. This is palpably <hi>ſelf evident.</hi> Whence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:65387:27"/>the <hi>Third;</hi> and <hi>therefore they are infallible. R. p.</hi> 47.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>But unleſs the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Tradition</hi> which they <hi>follow</hi> be longer than it is yet proved to be, they may follow it, and <hi>err</hi> all along by following it. <hi>A. p.</hi> 21.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>No doubt of it. <hi>R. p.</hi> 47.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Then prove it to be of ſufficient <hi>length.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>As if we had never proved our <hi>Tradition</hi> reaches to our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s days. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I know not when. Suppoſe you had, that's not all: for let it be never ſo <hi>long,</hi> yet if you <hi>follow</hi> it <hi>not,</hi> you may <hi>err;</hi> and therefore are not <hi>infallible,</hi> except you ſhew you <hi>cannot chuſe</hi> but <hi>follow</hi> it. <hi>A. p.</hi> 21.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Fourth Propoſition</hi> brought to prove that this <hi>Tradition</hi> we lay claim to, does indeed reach to <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> is this: <hi>They could not innovate in Faith, unleſs they did forget what they held the day before, or out of malice alter it. R. p.</hi> 48.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>You undertake to make this out more clearly, (<hi>L. p.</hi> 18.) and therefore I would hear what you ſay there for our better Information. <hi>A. p.</hi> 21.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>This is a moſt <hi>evident</hi> and a moſt <hi>unconſcionable Falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication:</hi> clear your Credit when you can, I charge it upon you as a <hi>voluntary inſincerity. R. p.</hi> 48, 49.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Good words, I pray, Sir. What is it I have done?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You have directly <hi>falfified</hi> that <hi>whole Diſcourſe,</hi> by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending here that the <hi>words</hi> you <hi>cite,</hi> were to <hi>make out</hi> that <hi>Fourth Propoſition</hi> clearly; whereas the truth of that <hi>Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> was <hi>made out</hi> by me. <hi>L. p.</hi> 9.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I ſaw it, Sir, and ſpake to it too, as I ſhall ſhew anon. What are thoſe <hi>words</hi> of yours I <hi>cite?</hi> Recite them, I pray, and I'll recite my <hi>Anſwers</hi> to them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Did</hi> Chriſt <hi>teach any Error? L. p.</hi> 18.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>He did not. <hi>A. p.</hi> 21.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>When a Father believ'd what</hi> Chriſt <hi>taught him, and the Son what the Father believ'd, did not the Son too believe what</hi> Chriſt <hi>taught? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:65387:27"/>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>No doubt of it but he did. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Run it on to the last Son that ſhall be born in the World, must not every one believe what</hi> Chriſt <hi>taught, if every one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd what his Father believ'd? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It is certain he muſt. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And will you then go about to perſwade us that there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually is a company of men in the World, who adher'd to this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, all Sons believing always as their Fathers did, whereof the first believ'd as</hi> Chriſt <hi>taught, and who notwithſtanding err'd in matters of Faith?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>No, you may be ſure on't. Theſe then are <hi>your words</hi> I <hi>cited.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>This <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> was level'd at a <hi>quite different</hi> buſineſs, viz. <hi>That a Church could not adhere to Tradition, and err in Faith at the ſame time.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis true, and I ſaw it, that this was it you there <hi>made out;</hi> but I do not yet ſee how it is a <hi>quite different</hi> buſineſs from that which I ſaid you <hi>undertook</hi> to <hi>make out</hi> more clearly. It was not <hi>proving</hi> I meant by <hi>making out</hi> more clearly, but <hi>illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating</hi> or <hi>explaining;</hi> nor was it the <hi>whole</hi> (which, according to you, conſiſts of a <hi>Propoſition</hi> and its <hi>proof</hi>) but the <hi>Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> only I ſaid you <hi>undertook</hi> there to <hi>illuſtrate;</hi> and therefore I would not proceed to the <hi>proof</hi> which you would ſeem to <hi>make out</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 9.) till I had conſider'd how you <hi>explain'd</hi> the <hi>Propoſition</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 18.): which after I had done, I came to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine your <hi>proof</hi> (as you call it) both as it is <hi>p.</hi> 9. and as you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain talk of it, <hi>p.</hi> 32. This you ſaw, <hi>A. p.</hi> 23. Where then lies the <hi>Falſification?</hi> The <hi>Propoſition</hi> is, <hi>They could not innovate in Faith.</hi> Who are <hi>they</hi> that cannot? <hi>Traditionary Chriſtians.</hi> And who are theſe? <hi>They that hold the ſame to day, which they did yeſterday,</hi> &amp;c. What cannot theſe do? <hi>They cannot inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate,</hi> or <hi>err in Faith.</hi> So ſay I you explain it (<hi>p.</hi> 18.) And do you not ſo, though it was upon another occaſion? Do you not ſhew, that <hi>if they hold to Tradition,</hi> or be <hi>Traditionary Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> they cannot, <hi>whilst</hi> they <hi>are ſo,</hi> (and when they are <hi>not ſo,</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:65387:28"/>they are none of the <hi>they</hi> in the <hi>Propoſition) innovate</hi> or <hi>err in Faith? Overcharging</hi> often occaſions <hi>recoiling;</hi> and if your <hi>Conſcience</hi> feel it not, ſo much the worſe.</p>
               <p>And now after all this noiſe, <hi>one little thing</hi> is yet to be <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> viz. <hi>That theſe</hi> Traditionary Chriſtians <hi>adhere</hi> undeclining<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>to an</hi> unqueſtionable Tradition, <hi>deſcending</hi> really <hi>and</hi> unvari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably <hi>from</hi> Chriſt <hi>and his</hi> Apoſtles, <hi>and could not</hi> poſſibly <hi>do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe;</hi> that is, <hi>that they neither did nor could err from the Faith firſt taught, for this is but ſuppoſed hitherto. A. p.</hi> 22.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Was it not <hi>proved</hi> in the <hi>Fourth Propoſition,</hi> and by me? <hi>p.</hi> 9? <hi>R. p.</hi> 51.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>At your rate it may be. <hi>And from this</hi> ſelf-evident Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, <hi>you</hi> neceſſarily <hi>conclude thus—Suppoſe</hi> Traditionary Chriſtians <hi>neither did nor could err, it is certain, they neither did nor could err.</hi> Make what more you can of it. <hi>A. p.</hi> 22.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You <hi>falſifie</hi> our words, who ever ſaid a <hi>Suppoſition</hi> is <hi>ſelf-evident? R. p.</hi> 52.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Who ever ſaid you did? May I not uſe an <hi>Irony,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the guilt of <hi>falſifying?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You <hi>falſifie</hi> again, in affirming that from this <hi>ſelf-evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Suppoſition,</hi> I <hi>neceſſarily</hi> conclude, <hi>&amp;c. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Juſt as before, in ſaying you <hi>neceſſarily conclude</hi> from a <hi>ſelf-evident Suppoſition.</hi> I ſay, all you conclude, amounts to no more. And make you what more you can of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Our entire <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> runs thus, if we muſt needs put it into <hi>form</hi> for you: <hi>Thoſe who adhere to</hi> Tradition <hi>all along from the beginning, neither did nor could err in</hi> Faith. <hi>R. p.</hi> 53.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>No, not if it was <hi>true Apoſtolical Tradition,</hi> and they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered <hi>wholly</hi> and <hi>ſolely</hi> to it, doing ſo they <hi>did</hi> not, <hi>could</hi> not err.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Roman Catholick Church <hi>does now, and did from time to time adhere to Tradition. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>To <hi>Apoſtolical Tradition wholly</hi> and <hi>only?</hi> I deny that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>They could not innovate in</hi> Faith, <hi>unleſs they did</hi> forget <hi>what they held the day before, or out of</hi> malice <hi>alter it. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>You hope then we can have no advantage by pleading
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:65387:28"/>either of theſe, in barr to the <hi>Infallibility</hi> of <hi>Tradition. A.</hi> 22.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You do not, I ſuppoſe, deſire we ſhould prove, that Men had always <hi>memories,</hi> or that <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were never ſo <hi>malicious,</hi> as to damn themſelves and their poſterity <hi>wittingly;</hi> and yet it can ſtick no where elſe. <hi>L p.</hi> 32.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Were there no danger of Mens <hi>forgetting</hi> what had been taught, 'tis hard to ſay, why the <hi>Pen-men</hi> of the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſhould have been at the <hi>needleſs</hi> pains to <hi>write</hi> it. <hi>A. p.</hi> 23.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Your Diſcourſe is this. <hi>'Tis hard to ſay, That</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians <hi>ſhould have remembred their Teſterday's Faith, had not the</hi> Scripture <hi>been written. R. p.</hi> 54.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>As thô to remember it from <hi>Night</hi> to <hi>Morning</hi> were enough. I ſay, 'tis hard to ſay, why the <hi>Scripture</hi> was written, if men might in no Age <hi>forget</hi> what had been taught.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Reaſons</hi> why <hi>Scripture</hi> was written, you might have read in <hi>St. Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16, 17. Where there is no ſuch thing, as to make men <hi>remember their Yeſterday's Faith,</hi> nor that <hi>Scripture</hi> is of <hi>neceſſity</hi> at all, but only that it is <hi>profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> for many <hi>uſes</hi> there enumerated. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I know how unwilling ſome of you are that <hi>Scripture</hi> ſhould be thought <hi>neceſſary</hi> at all, and alſo how much <hi>aſhamed</hi> they are to ſay it is <hi>unneceſſary</hi> altogether. Let it be (as you ſay) only <hi>Profitable</hi> for <hi>Doctrine, Reproof, Correction, Inſtruction:</hi> For my part, if men once <hi>taught</hi> the <hi>Faith</hi> can never <hi>forget</hi> it; If <hi>Oral Tradition</hi> can do <hi>all</hi> this without <hi>Scripture,</hi> and <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> nothing of <hi>all</hi> this without <hi>Tradition,</hi> I think it is wholly <hi>uſeleſs</hi> and <hi>unprofitable,</hi> and therefore ſee no <hi>reaſon</hi> it ſhould be <hi>written.</hi> And yet if mens <hi>memories</hi> be ſo very faithful, <hi>St. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſeems to me to have been <hi>too forgetful</hi> of it, when with ſo much earneſtneſs he endeavour'd, that men might be able after his deceaſe to have theſe things always in <hi>remembrance,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1, 15. and that by leaving them in <hi>writing. A. p.</hi> 23.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>There is not ſo much as one word in the whole Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter concerning the <hi>remembring</hi> or <hi>forgetting</hi> their <hi>Faith,</hi> but of <hi>remembring</hi> his particular <hi>exhortations to good life. R. p.</hi> 55.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:65387:29"/>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Neither ſaid I there was; it was enough for me to prove hence, that men might <hi>forget what they had been taught:</hi> and if an <hi>exhortation</hi> to <hi>good life,</hi> why not an <hi>Article</hi> of <hi>Faith?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Notwithſtanding all you have anſwer'd, men had <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory enough</hi> not to <hi>forget</hi> their <hi>yeſterday's Faith. R. p.</hi> 56.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Well, at preſent ſuppoſe it. Why might they not have <hi>Malice</hi> enough to <hi>alter</hi> or <hi>corrupt</hi> it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Were <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſo <hi>malicious</hi> as to damn themſelves and their poſterity <hi>wittingly?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>May they not be as careleſs of preſerving the <hi>Faith,</hi> as of maintaining <hi>Holineſs</hi> in themſelves and their poſterity, when they know that <hi>Sin</hi> is as <hi>damnable</hi> as <hi>Error? A. p.</hi> 23.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Be Judge your ſelf. Do not many of your <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſin often,</hi> and yet <hi>few</hi> or <hi>none</hi> of them <hi>deſert</hi> their <hi>Faith once? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I grant men may <hi>often ſin,</hi> yet be neither <hi>Apoſtates</hi> not <hi>Hereticks.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Reaſons</hi> why the <hi>Parallel</hi> holds not are theſe. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Word</hi> of an <hi>Infallible Inſtructer</hi> ſhall paſs with me for a <hi>thouſand Reaſons.</hi> Tell me only what theſe <hi>Reaſons</hi> prove, it will ſuffice. If it be this, that men may <hi>ſin often,</hi> and yet not <hi>deſert</hi> their <hi>Faith,</hi> 'tis already granted. Is it any thing elſe you would prove by them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>My Reaſons thwart the <hi>univerſal alteration</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> while <hi>Chriſtians</hi> proceeded on the former <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Tradition. R. p.</hi> 59.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis granted alſo, that <hi>Chriſtians</hi> adhering to <hi>Apoſtolical Tradition,</hi> there could be no <hi>univerſal alteration</hi> of <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>They clearly evince an <hi>univerſal change</hi> in the <hi>Rule of Faith</hi> over the <hi>whole Body</hi> of <hi>Believers</hi> is abſolutely impracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable. <hi>R. p.</hi> 57.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Whatever your Reaſons evince, we grant ſuch an <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal change</hi> will never be, becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> will always have a <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>true Believers.</hi> But why might not a <hi>conſiderable part</hi> of the <hi>Whole Body</hi> alter the <hi>Faith</hi> firſt taught?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:65387:29"/>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The change muſt be <hi>profeſſed</hi> and <hi>open,</hi> otherwiſe it <hi>alters</hi> not the caſe; and <hi>poſterity</hi> will believe ſtill on, according as things appear outwardly. <hi>R p.</hi> 56.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Men may <hi>change</hi> the <hi>Faith,</hi> and at firſt <hi>privately</hi> teach it to a few, not <hi>profeſſing</hi> at all that they <hi>change</hi> it, but that they <hi>retrieve</hi> it, after a <hi>change</hi> had been made in it; and they who are taught it, may believe it and ſpread it, and it may at laſt be <hi>openly profeſs'd,</hi> without <hi>profeſſing</hi> a <hi>change</hi> from what it was at firſt, which is not the wont of <hi>Hereticks.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Not unleſs it be ſaid they went conſcienciouſly upon ſome <hi>other ground</hi> than <hi>Tradition. R. p.</hi> 57.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>And why might they not do ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis impoſſible they ſhould take up <hi>another ground. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Your reaſon I pray.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe if they could not <hi>innovate in Faith,</hi> they could not innovate in <hi>that</hi> upon which they held <hi>all</hi> their <hi>Faith. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Very good. You were proving they cannot <hi>innovate in Faith,</hi> becauſe they <hi>adhere</hi> to <hi>Tradition;</hi> now you prove they muſt <hi>adhere</hi> to <hi>Tradition,</hi> becauſe they cannot <hi>innovate</hi> in <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Men are more <hi>tenacious</hi> of their <hi>Principles</hi>—, than they are to <hi>relinquiſh</hi> all they have <hi>receiv'd</hi> upon thoſe <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>That which they hold upon the <hi>Principle</hi> of <hi>Tradition</hi> is <hi>all their Faith,</hi> and you ſaid but now, the <hi>care</hi> of their <hi>Faith</hi> made them hold their <hi>Principles;</hi> now you ſay, they are <hi>leſs careful</hi> of their <hi>Faith,</hi> than of their <hi>Principles.</hi> Thus have we <hi>Circle</hi> after <hi>Circle.</hi> Why would they hold their <hi>Rule</hi> or <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple?</hi> Becauſe they were render of their <hi>Faith.</hi> Why were they ſo tender of their <hi>Faith?</hi> Becauſe they were more tender of their <hi>Rule</hi> or <hi>Principle.</hi> I ask not, how men may be proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called, <hi>Tenacious to relinquiſh:</hi> but pick the beſt ſenſe I can out of your pure non-ſenſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tradition</hi> is the <hi>Authority</hi> of the whole <hi>Eccleſia do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens</hi>—, which could never permit it ſelf to be thought to have <hi>atteſted</hi> a <hi>lye</hi> hitherto. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:65387:30"/>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>If <hi>Tradition</hi> be the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> then (as you ſaid of that <hi>Authority</hi>) it is of no more <hi>credit,</hi> than a ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry told by an <hi>old woman,</hi> till better <hi>reaſons</hi> be given for it; nor hath it this <hi>effect</hi> upon <hi>Humane Nature</hi> by its <hi>own proper Power,</hi> to prove <hi>Truth.</hi> But why may not the whole <hi>Eccleſia docens</hi> (ſuppoſing it the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome) attest</hi> to a <hi>lye?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>It could never <hi>permit</hi> it ſelf (were there nothing but its own <hi>intereſt</hi>) to be <hi>thought</hi> to do it. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay well, <hi>not to be</hi> thought <hi>to do it,</hi> for that would ſpoil all: Thô I know not how it can be hinder'd, but ſome will <hi>think</hi> ſo, It might be its <hi>Intereſt</hi> to <hi>advance it ſelf,</hi> and for that, to pretend a <hi>falſe Tradition,</hi> and to <hi>forge evidences</hi> to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten a <hi>lye</hi> on former Ages.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>None could be <hi>competent Judges,</hi> what was fit to be a <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> but <hi>they</hi> who were ſo concern'd both in <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Intereſt, Tradition</hi> ſhould not be ſet aſide. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Then if <hi>Intereſt</hi> prevail'd above <hi>Duty,</hi> a <hi>falſe Tradition</hi> might be pretended, and the World muſt receive it on <hi>their credit,</hi> becauſe <hi>they alone</hi> are to be accounted <hi>competent Judges.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>There muſt be ſome <hi>great time</hi> betwixt their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carding <hi>Tradition,</hi> and eſpouſing a <hi>New Rule;</hi> during which time we muſt imagine the whole <hi>Church</hi> (except perhaps ſome <hi>few</hi> that diſcover'd it firſt) would be made up of <hi>Seekers,</hi> ſome hovering one way, ſome another; in which caſe they would as yet have no <hi>Faith,</hi> and conſequently there could be no <hi>Church. R. p.</hi> 57, 58.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>No, Sir, a <hi>pretence</hi> to <hi>Tradition</hi> as the <hi>only Rule</hi> might ſtill be kept afoot, and yet <hi>changes</hi> made in <hi>Points</hi> of <hi>Faith:</hi> whil'ſt they who <hi>publickly oppos'd</hi> or <hi>privately diſown'd</hi> them, adhering only to the <hi>true Apoſtolical Tradition,</hi> were the <hi>true Church.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>If they could <hi>innovate</hi> in <hi>Faith,</hi> they muſt <hi>pretend</hi> to <hi>Tradition</hi> ſtill, when they had <hi>evidently deſerted it,</hi> that is, They muſt <hi>profeſs</hi> to hold the <hi>Teſterday's Faith,</hi> when all the World muſt ſee, and every one's own heart muſt tell him the <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> Which is the higheſt <hi>impoſſibility. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:65387:30"/>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>They might <hi>pretend</hi> to <hi>Tradition,</hi> when <hi>evidently</hi> to <hi>others,</hi> they had <hi>deſerted</hi> it in many things; and ſome of them, not <hi>impoſſibly,</hi> when their <hi>own hearts</hi> told them ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis <hi>impoſſible</hi> any <hi>Temptations</hi> ſhould move all men, to fall into this <hi>one ſin</hi> of <hi>altering</hi> the <hi>Faith. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>How <hi>impoſſible</hi> I know not, but I think it neither ever <hi>did</hi> or <hi>ſhall</hi> come to paſs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Summing up my Diſcourſe, (<hi>Sect.</hi> 45.) 'tis manifeſt, you have no way to <hi>anſwer</hi> our <hi>Argument,</hi> but by <hi>ſuppoſing</hi> there was a time, in which there were no conſiderable Body of Men in the World either <hi>good Chriſtians, honeſt Men,</hi> or <hi>valuing</hi> their <hi>credit;</hi> but only a company of <hi>Brutiſh, Godleſs, Lying Ruſſians,</hi> without the leaſt degree of <hi>Grace</hi> or <hi>Shame</hi> in <hi>them. R. p.</hi> 60.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It is then <hi>unanſwerable</hi> by me, for I cannot <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> this. Thô I am not convinced that Men cannot <hi>innovate</hi> in <hi>Faith,</hi> till it be ſhewn, not only that they have <hi>memory enough</hi> to remember <hi>Teſterday's</hi> teaching; but that they made a <hi>right uſe</hi> of their <hi>Memory</hi> to that purpoſe; and farther, that they had ſo <hi>little wickedneſs,</hi> as not only not <hi>wittingly</hi> to damn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their poſterity, but as not to <hi>neglect</hi> any <hi>care</hi> that ſhould be taken for their <hi>ſalvation;</hi> and <hi>many things</hi> more not yet ſhewn. For, what if <hi>all</hi> Sons did not <hi>underſtand aright</hi> all that Fathers had taught them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>If <hi>all</hi> did not, moſt of the <hi>intelligent Paſters</hi> would, and could eaſily <hi>inſtruct</hi> them, it being both ſo <hi>obligatory</hi> and ſo <hi>eaſie. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obligatory</hi> indeed, yet not ſo <hi>eaſie</hi> ſo to <hi>inſtruct</hi> them as to <hi>convince</hi> them; as you, I doubt not, find it in thoſe whom you ſuppoſe in error. Suppoſe again, ſome Sons were ſo <hi>negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent</hi> as to take no <hi>care</hi> either to <hi>remember</hi> or <hi>teach</hi> what they had been taught by their Fathers?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Then the <hi>diligent</hi> would <hi>reprehend</hi> them, and ſee things <hi>amended;</hi> and thoſe <hi>careleſs</hi> Perſons, eſpecially if <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors,</hi> reduced to their Duty, there being <hi>Orders</hi> on foot in the World to oblige them to it. <hi>R. p.</hi> 61.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:65387:31"/>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>How came it to paſs then, that all <hi>Hereticks</hi> were not long ago <hi>ſuppreſſed?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis an unheard of <hi>Negligence,</hi> not to know or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Yeſterday's Faith. R. p.</hi> 61.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>But 'tis a very <hi>poſſible</hi> thing, either not to <hi>heed</hi> what is <hi>taught</hi> to <hi>day,</hi> and ſo to be <hi>ignorant</hi> of it to <hi>morrow;</hi> or not to remember to <hi>morrow</hi> every thing that is taught to <hi>day;</hi> or being taught to <hi>day,</hi> to think of it no more to <hi>morrow,</hi> nor <hi>many days</hi> after, and to <hi>forget</hi> ſomething of it at laſt. But what if ſome through <hi>Ambition, Vain-glory,</hi> and <hi>Popularity,</hi> ſet abroach <hi>New Doctrines,</hi> and taught them for <hi>Apoſtolical Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Good men would ſet themſelves to <hi>oppoſe</hi> them, make known their <hi>Pretences,</hi> and lay open their <hi>Novelties. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I doubt it not; but not always ſo <hi>effectually,</hi> as the <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors</hi> ſhould not have many <hi>followers.</hi> What if others to <hi>ſave</hi> themſelves from <hi>Perſecution, conceal'd</hi> part, and <hi>corrupted</hi> more of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> by their <hi>own Traditions?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Others would <hi>oppoſe</hi> their <hi>unchriſtian</hi> proceedings, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal</hi> what they had <hi>conceal'd, reſtore</hi> what they had <hi>corrupted,</hi> and <hi>manifest</hi> that Doctrine they <hi>ſubintroduced</hi> had not <hi>deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> by the <hi>chanel</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Church's Tradition. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yet here's <hi>Tradition</hi> pretended againſt <hi>Tradition,</hi> and many, it may be, carried away with the <hi>Pretence;</hi> and a <hi>great number</hi> (as you have ſaid) <hi>atteſting,</hi> the <hi>atteſtation</hi> is to be thought <hi>ſufficient;</hi> and then a <hi>greater number</hi> can add nothing to it. Let others then <hi>oppoſe</hi> and <hi>manifest</hi> what they can, <hi>all</hi> poſſibly will not be <hi>convinced.</hi> What if others through a <hi>blind zeal, ignorant devotion, ſuperſtitious rigour,</hi> and <hi>vain credulity, added</hi> many things to the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> which by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees grew into more <hi>general eſteem,</hi> till at laſt they were <hi>own'd,</hi> and <hi>impoſed</hi> as <hi>neceſſary</hi> to be <hi>believ'd</hi> and <hi>practiced?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>If they belong'd to <hi>Faith</hi> they could not come in, while the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Tradition</hi> was <hi>adher'd</hi> to, as has been prov'd and granted. <hi>R. p.</hi> 62.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:65387:31"/>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>True, not whilſt <hi>Apoſtolical Tradition wholly</hi> and <hi>ſolely</hi> was <hi>adher'd</hi> to by <hi>All,</hi> whether they belong'd to <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>no.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Perhaps <hi>ſome Points</hi> involv'd in the <hi>main Body</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> not yet ſo <hi>explicitly</hi> or <hi>univerſally</hi> known, might, on <hi>emergent occaſions</hi> be <hi>ſingled</hi> out, <hi>defin'd,</hi> and more eſpecially <hi>recommended</hi> than formerly, without any <hi>detriment</hi> to the <hi>Faith</hi> receiv'd, but rather to the <hi>advantage</hi> and farther <hi>explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of it. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I underſtand you thus. <hi>All</hi> Points of <hi>Faith</hi> are no more <hi>explicitly</hi> convey'd to us by <hi>Tradition,</hi> than by <hi>Scripture;</hi> but ſome of them <hi>implicitly</hi> only. 'Tis ſomething <hi>elſe</hi> which hath <hi>all</hi> in its <hi>breast,</hi> and by <hi>degrees</hi> vents it in <hi>parcels,</hi> as there is <hi>occcaſion</hi> to <hi>define</hi> and <hi>recommend;</hi> and then, thô men might before be <hi>ſaved, without</hi> the <hi>knowledge</hi> of it, it becomes as <hi>neceſſary</hi> an <hi>Article</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> as any of the <hi>rest.</hi> This is the great <hi>Myſtery,</hi> had <hi>all</hi> been given out at <hi>first,</hi> the <hi>Box</hi> being <hi>empty,</hi> would have been in ſome danger to have been <hi>laid aſide</hi> and <hi>diſregarded.</hi> Well, but after all this, If ſomebody ſhould ſtart up and ſay, <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that Article</hi> thus <hi>defined</hi> is no part of the <hi>old Apoſtolical Tradition,</hi> but a meer <hi>innovation,</hi> who muſt <hi>decide</hi> the matter? Who but the <hi>Church?</hi> All <hi>Truth</hi> is lodg'd in her <hi>breast.</hi> But which is this <hi>Church?</hi> That which holds to <hi>Tradition,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome:</hi> Which is the <hi>true Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> That which the <hi>Church; viz.</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> holds. What now if <hi>Error</hi> any of the former <hi>Ways</hi> brought forth, <hi>grew, multipli'd, ſpread,</hi> obtain'd moſt <hi>power,</hi> and drove <hi>out</hi> all that held the <hi>naked truth</hi> from all thoſe <hi>Countreys</hi> where it came?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Do any <hi>Hiſtories</hi> tell you, This <hi>Error</hi> ſpread over the <hi>Whole Church,</hi> without your ſuppoſing the <hi>Queſtion,</hi> that <hi>ſuch</hi> or <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>Tenet</hi> is an <hi>Error,</hi> which you <hi>pretend</hi> ſuch; which is above the skill of <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> to decide, and is only to be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd by examining <hi>first who have, who have not a certain Rule of Faith? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Over the <hi>Whole Church</hi> is too much. <hi>Hiſtories</hi> tell us of the ſpreading of <hi>Error,</hi> ſuch as both <hi>You</hi> and <hi>We</hi> account
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:65387:32"/>ſo, over divers <hi>Countreys.</hi> What need is there of <hi>ſuppoſing</hi> the <hi>Queſtion,</hi> that <hi>ſuch</hi> or <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>Tenet</hi> is an <hi>Error,</hi> betwixt <hi>us</hi> who are <hi>agreed</hi> about it, as I think we are in that of <hi>Arianiſm?</hi> But as to what you add, pray tell me. If <hi>Tradition</hi> be the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> who can be <hi>fitter</hi> to <hi>decide</hi> what <hi>Tenet</hi> is <hi>Error</hi> than <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> who ſhould know beſt what belongs to <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ages?</hi> But I forget, 'tis the <hi>Oral Tradition</hi> of the <hi>prefent Church</hi> is your <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> have to do on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with things <hi>past:</hi> and I agree with you, that it exceeds their <hi>Skill</hi> to ſhew us, that <hi>all thoſe things</hi> which your <hi>preſent Church</hi> calls <hi>Errors,</hi> were decided to be ſuch in the <hi>first Ages.</hi> However, ſeeing what is <hi>Error</hi> is only to be <hi>decided</hi> by <hi>exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining</hi> firſt <hi>who have, who have not a certain Rule of Faith,</hi> I beſeech you be not ſo haſty, as you uſe to be, to call us <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> whil'ſt this Point is but yet under <hi>examination.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>But what are all theſe <hi>rambling Queſtions</hi> to our <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which inſiſts on the <hi>impoſſibility</hi> of <hi>altering</hi> the <hi>Yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day's Faith,</hi> but either out of want of <hi>Memory,</hi> or out of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice? R. p.</hi> 62, 63.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>They <hi>ramble home</hi> to your <hi>Argument,</hi> where you would not ſee them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Apply them to <hi>this,</hi> and they loſe all their <hi>force. Ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>If <hi>Faith</hi> may be <hi>alter'd all</hi> or <hi>any</hi> of theſe <hi>Ways,</hi> then, if <hi>they all</hi> ſhould imply <hi>forgetfulneſs</hi> or <hi>malice,</hi> (as you ſay <hi>moſt</hi> of them do in ſome degree) men may through <hi>forgetfulneſs</hi> or <hi>malice innovate in Faith;</hi> and if they imply <hi>neither,</hi> men may <hi>innovate</hi> otherwiſe than through <hi>forgetfulneſs</hi> or <hi>malice.</hi> Either way your <hi>Arguments</hi> ſpoil'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I long to ſee't made out, that an <hi>erring Church</hi> can ſtill <hi>plead Tradition,</hi> and <hi>adhere</hi> to it. <hi>L. p.</hi> 18.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>That an <hi>erring Church adheres</hi> (as I have formerly ſaid) to <hi>Tradition,</hi> I know no man that will undertake to make out to ſave your longing. But may not a <hi>Church</hi> that once <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her'd</hi> to <hi>Tradition,</hi> leave it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:65387:32"/>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>That a <hi>Church</hi> may <hi>follow Tradition</hi> at one time, and <hi>leave</hi> it at another, is no news. <hi>L. p.</hi> 15.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>If this be no News, then though we ſhould grant <hi>Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to be an <hi>infallible</hi> conveyance of the <hi>Truth,</hi> yet would it not make even <hi>that Church</hi> which <hi>now adheres</hi> to it <hi>iufallible;</hi> and therefore the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> (though we ſhould confeſs her at <hi>preſent</hi> to <hi>adhere</hi> to <hi>infallible Tradition</hi>) could not <hi>prove</hi> her ſelf thereby to be <hi>infallible.</hi> That <hi>Church</hi> only is <hi>infallible,</hi> which <hi>cannot err;</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> that at one time <hi>follows Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> may <hi>leave it</hi> at another, and ſo doing <hi>errs.</hi> Therefore if the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> will be <hi>infallible,</hi> ſhe muſt prove not only, that ſhe <hi>follows Tradition,</hi> for ſo ſhe proves only, that ſhe <hi>does not err;</hi> but alſo that ſhe <hi>cannot leave</hi> it, for <hi>infallibility</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes all <hi>poſſibility</hi> of <hi>erring,</hi> by <hi>leaving Tradition.</hi> She muſt therefore ſeek out a new <hi>Medium</hi> to prove her ſelf <hi>infallible. A. p.</hi> 25.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Do not you ſee this already <hi>proved</hi> to your hand? <hi>R. p.</hi> 63.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>No, truly, and I deſpair of ever hearing <hi>him</hi> prove, that a <hi>Church</hi> which now follows <hi>Tradition,</hi> cannot leave it, <hi>who</hi> has told me, 'tis <hi>no News,</hi> but a <hi>common caſe,</hi> for a <hi>Church</hi> that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows it, to leave it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Not to repeat the many <hi>Reaſons</hi> produced for <hi>this point,</hi> Sect. 45. <hi>R p.</hi> 63.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>You did not ſure mean, <hi>I ſaw it proved to my hand</hi> in thoſe <hi>Reaſons</hi> which you had not <hi>then produced.</hi> And I ſee as little yet, that they were <hi>produced</hi> for <hi>this point.</hi> I granted you <hi>all that</hi> for which you told me you <hi>produced</hi> them, when you mention'd them, but that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> cannot <hi>leave Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> was not it you then told me you produced them for.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Innovation</hi> and <hi>Tradition</hi> being <hi>formally</hi> and <hi>diametri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi> oppoſite, what proves ſhe could not <hi>innovate,</hi> proves alſo that ſhe could not <hi>leave Tradition,</hi> for this were to <hi>innovate R. p.</hi> 63.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>But where was it proved ſhe could not <hi>innovate?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:65387:33"/>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Our <hi>Argument</hi> you ſee has <hi>already proved</hi> it. I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you ſhould diſſemble a thing ſo <hi>obvious,</hi> and run forwards upon that <hi>affected inadvertence</hi> of yours. 'Tis the very thing our <hi>Argument</hi> chieſly aims at. <hi>R. p.</hi> 63, 64.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aiming</hi> and <hi>hitting</hi> are two things; you ſay it <hi>aim'd</hi> at it, but I have ſhewn you it <hi>miſs'd</hi> it. And farther I tell you, that if ever you <hi>hit</hi> it, you will <hi>wound</hi> your ſelf. Will you prove a <hi>Church</hi> that <hi>follows Tradition cannot leave it,</hi> and yet ſay the <hi>contradictory</hi> to it is <hi>true?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You would perſwade us rather to prove our <hi>Church</hi> free from <hi>Error. R. p.</hi> 64.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I think it good advice, and for your encouragement have told you, that I think we are <hi>obliged</hi> (whenever you prove it) to be of her <hi>Communion.</hi> Will you not take my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to make us your <hi>Converts?</hi> I ſaid alſo, 'tis the <hi>eaſier</hi> task for you, if ſhe be ſo; and if ſhe be not <hi>ſo,</hi> you <hi>in vain attempt</hi> to prove her <hi>more</hi> than ſo, <hi>infallible.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Your wiſe advice amounts to this, that you would have us prove our <hi>concluſion,</hi> without beginning with our <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>No, but that you would be content with a <hi>concluſion eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> to be prov'd, and <hi>enough</hi> for you when proved; and that you would prove it by <hi>better Premiſes, better known</hi> than the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>All our <hi>Faith</hi> may be <hi>Error,</hi> if the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> (our <hi>Rule</hi>) may be <hi>erroneous;</hi> and if it cannot, nothing we hold of <hi>Faith</hi> can be ſo. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Then either the <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> may be <hi>Error,</hi> or <hi>yours</hi> is not the <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> May the <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> be <hi>all Error,</hi> if the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> can <hi>err</hi> in her <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> then doth it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on the <hi>Infallibility</hi> of your <hi>Church</hi> for its <hi>truth,</hi> not on <hi>Chriſt's Veracity.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Your meaning is, we ſhould only <hi>prove</hi> ſhe embraces no <hi>Error now;</hi> but what <hi>proviſion</hi> would this make, for her not falling perhaps into <hi>Error</hi> to <hi>morrow? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:65387:33"/>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Againſt the <hi>poſſibility</hi> of her falling into <hi>Error hereafter,</hi> I know of no <hi>proviſion</hi> can be made; but to be <hi>ſure</hi> ſhe does not <hi>err</hi> at <hi>preſent,</hi> is the beſt <hi>ſecurity</hi> ſhe can have, and (to <hi>you</hi>) muſt needs be good enough: for ſure you will not have it ſaid your <hi>Church</hi> can be guilty of ſo unheard-of a <hi>Negligence</hi> as to forget to <hi>morrow</hi> her <hi>yeſterdays Faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Were our <hi>Rule</hi> granted <hi>fallible,</hi> by what more <hi>certain way</hi> could we be directed to arrive at <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>ſenſe? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Take the plain <hi>Scripture</hi> for your <hi>Rule.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>However, your <hi>counſel</hi> ſuits better with your <hi>conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,</hi> than theſe crabbed <hi>Demonſtrations. R. p.</hi> 65.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Yours are indeed <hi>crabbed</hi> enough, and <hi>plain Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> would ſuit better with Infallibility. But why will you la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to no purpoſe? All the World knows that a ſingle <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> in one <hi>Error,</hi> is enough to <hi>anſwer</hi> all the <hi>Arguments</hi> can be brought for her <hi>Infallibility,</hi> ſeeing it muſt needs be falſe to ſay ſhe <hi>cannot err,</hi> who in any one thing <hi>doth err. A.p.</hi> 25.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>If the <hi>Premiſes</hi> be <hi>right</hi> and the <hi>Inference good,</hi> the <hi>concluſion</hi> muſt be neceſſarily <hi>true. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I grant it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>First</hi> then you are to <hi>anſwer</hi> our <hi>Argument,</hi> and next to ſee the <hi>Authority</hi> that qualifies your <hi>Inſtance</hi> for an <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> be above <hi>Moral certainty. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Your <hi>Arguments</hi> are not hard to <hi>anſwer,</hi> yet if I could not anſwer an <hi>Argument</hi> brought by ſome cunning <hi>Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> to prove, that <hi>Men</hi> can know as <hi>certainly</hi> as <hi>God,</hi> though ſome <hi>Scholar</hi> might laugh at me, no <hi>Chriſtian</hi> would do ſo. If an <hi>Inſtance</hi> lie before me, ſo <hi>certain</hi> as there is no juſt cauſe to <hi>doubt</hi> of it, which is <hi>Moral certainty,</hi> it is enough to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie me an <hi>Argument</hi> which <hi>contradicts</hi> it, it is falſe, though I may not be able to diſcern the <hi>Fallacy,</hi> and will always be enough for one that values the <hi>truth</hi> more than the <hi>credit</hi> of a <hi>Logician.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis the right of the <hi>Reſpondent,</hi> to deny any thing that is not driven up to <hi>Evidence. R. p.</hi> 66.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:65387:34"/>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis our <hi>Right</hi> then to deny an <hi>Argument</hi> to be good, ſo long as we have a clear <hi>inſtance</hi> againſt it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You ſeem ſo kind as not to undertake to prove that an <hi>Erring Church adheres to Tradition, if it be true Apoſtolical Tradition, and that it adhere to it wholly and ſolely. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis no <hi>kindneſs,</hi> Sir, but abſolute <hi>neceſſity,</hi> I cannot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to prove what I know can never be proved.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Do not you mean by <hi>Tradition,</hi> ſuch an one as is built upon <hi>living Voice and Practice? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I mean a <hi>Tradition</hi> coming down <hi>unvariably</hi> from the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> build it on what you pleaſe, or can, for me. I thought you had meant by it <hi>living Voice</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> and therefore know not well what you mean by its being <hi>built</hi> on them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Then you <hi>quit</hi> your <hi>own Rule,</hi> by <hi>requiring</hi> men ſhould <hi>adhere</hi> to the <hi>other wholly</hi> and <hi>ſolely,</hi> and admit that a <hi>Church adhering</hi> to ſuch a <hi>Rule,</hi> is not an <hi>erring Church. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>This is wonderful indeed! The <hi>later</hi> I admit, and have promiſed, that when you ſhew us ſuch a <hi>Church,</hi> we will be of her <hi>Communion,</hi> and yet not grant her <hi>Infallible,</hi> A. p. 26. But how do I <hi>quit</hi> our <hi>own Rule,</hi> or <hi>require</hi> men to <hi>adhere</hi> to ſuch <hi>Tradition wholly</hi> and <hi>ſolely?</hi> Is it in ſaying they do not <hi>err</hi> that <hi>adhere</hi> to it, on ſuppoſition they be <hi>ſure</hi> they <hi>have</hi> it? What a pleaſant Invention was this? When you are ſure of ſuch a <hi>Tradition,</hi> beſides <hi>Scripture,</hi> tell us of it, and we will embrace it willingly, as you were told before, <hi>A. p.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>It ſeems very odd to me, in the mean time, that men ſhould call us <hi>Hereticks</hi>—and yet prove their own <hi>Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> by an <hi>Argument;</hi> which, if it prove any thing to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, muſt prove that no man who hath been taught the <hi>Faith,</hi> can <hi>err</hi> from it, and ſtill withal confeſs that whole <hi>Churches</hi> may err. <hi>A. p.</hi> 26.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>How do you ſhew our <hi>Argument</hi> muſt prove this ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd <hi>Poſition? R. p.</hi> 67.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:65387:34"/>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I ſay not it <hi>must ſimply,</hi> but if it prove any thing to purpoſe: For if it prove not this, ſome may <hi>forget</hi> or <hi>alter</hi> their <hi>yeſterday's Faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Our <hi>Tenet</hi> is, that though not <hi>one ſingle man</hi> can <hi>err</hi> while he <hi>adheres</hi> to our <hi>Rule,</hi> yet even ſome <hi>particular Churches</hi> may <hi>leave</hi> off <hi>adhering</hi> to it, and ſo <hi>err</hi> in <hi>Faith. R. p.</hi> 67.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>How came you then to charge me ſo ſuriouſly with <hi>falfifying?</hi> Was not your <hi>Argument</hi> brought to prove, that <hi>Traditionary Chriſtians</hi> could not <hi>innovate</hi> in <hi>Faith?</hi> When could they not <hi>innovate?</hi> Whilſt they hold to <hi>Tradition,</hi> ſay you. And was not this it I ſaid you undertook to make out elſewhere? And do not you now confeſs 'twas the ſame? Surely you do, when you ſay they might err by <hi>lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> it. Yet then your Argument muſt prove this <hi>abſurd Poſition,</hi> as you call it, or it proves nothing to purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> taught one and the ſame Doctrine, <hi>Alterations,</hi> 'tis certain, have been made in this Doctrine; and therefore without diſpute ſome have believed and taught o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than men were at firſt taught, <hi>&amp;c. A. p.</hi> 26, 27.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Some particular Churches may err in Faith. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>You are then to ſhew what ſpecial Priviledge the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> hath above all other <hi>Churches</hi> that ſhe cannot err. You ſay, they of that <hi>Church</hi> believe the ſame to day they did yeſterday, and ſo upwards. We bid you prove it. You tell us, if they <hi>follow</hi> this <hi>Rule,</hi> they could never <hi>err</hi> in <hi>Faith.</hi> But did they follow this <hi>Rule?</hi> You ſay they did. And if we will not believe it, there's an end on't. <hi>A. p.</hi> 27.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>This is built on ſome few of your <hi>wilful Falſifications. R. p.</hi> 68.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>If men will believe you, there's an end on't again.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Where did we ever bring theſe words [<hi>if they follow'd this Rule</hi>] for a <hi>proof</hi> that they hold the ſame, <hi>&amp;c. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>You brought thoſe words as an <hi>Introduction</hi> to your <hi>Proof,</hi> which amounts to no more than <hi>your,</hi> or <hi>your Church's</hi> ſaying,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:65387:35"/>ſhe did follow it. And what ſay you more, I pray? Yes, ſay you, ſhe could not <hi>innovate.</hi> Why could ſhe not? If ſhe could, ſhe muſt either <hi>forget,</hi> or through <hi>malice</hi> alter it. Why not ſo, or ſome other way alter the Faith? You ſay you need not prove that men had always Memories, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What's all this, but to ſay, your Church has men of <hi>good Memories</hi> and <hi>little Malice?</hi> And ſo if we believe you, ſtill there's an end on't.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="dialogue">
            <head>The Fourth Dialogue.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>YOU <hi>Proteſtants</hi> give us only a <hi>general Latitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narian Rule,</hi> common to all the <hi>Hereſies</hi> in the World. <hi>L. p.</hi> 25.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scripture is our Rule,</hi> and it is and ought to be the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Rule</hi> to <hi>All,</hi> even to <hi>Hereticks,</hi> though they miſerably a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe it, and though I could tell you too of <hi>Hereticks</hi> that truſted more to <hi>your Rule</hi> than to <hi>ours. A p.</hi> 27.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Pray, Sir, uſe my words; I ſaid a <hi>common Rule</hi> to <hi>them</hi> and <hi>you. R. p.</hi> 71.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Your words were no more, but <hi>common to all the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies in the World.</hi> Indeed for <hi>Hereſies</hi> I ſaid <hi>Hereticks,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe though <hi>Scripture</hi> ought to be a <hi>Rule</hi> to <hi>Heretioks,</hi> whereby they may <hi>correct</hi> their <hi>Errors;</hi> yet ſounds it ill to ſay, as you do, that it is a <hi>Rule</hi> to all the <hi>Hereſies</hi> or <hi>Errors</hi> in the World. But let it be (as you will have it) <hi>common</hi> to <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</hi> I begin to hope by this, that you count <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> no <hi>Hereticks.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Can that be <hi>truly</hi> a <hi>Rule,</hi> which they <hi>direct</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by, and yet warp into <hi>Error? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It may be <hi>truly</hi> a <hi>Rule,</hi> yea and the <hi>only true Rule</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> though they who pretend to <hi>direct</hi> themſelves by it, err. And they <hi>warp into Error,</hi> whilſt, pretending to be <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected</hi> by it, they <hi>direct themſelves</hi> too much, and are not <hi>directed</hi> by <hi>it alone.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:65387:35"/>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Socinians</hi> will ſay the ſame of you. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I can eaſily believe they may. But <hi>truth</hi> depends not on <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that</hi> man's ſaying <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>How then ſhall this Quarrel be decided? <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>If no way now, yet by <hi>Him</hi> who gave the <hi>Rule,</hi> and will at laſt <hi>judge</hi> us according to it. In the mean time, the <hi>Church</hi> has done what it could to <hi>decide</hi> it, and hath given it for <hi>us.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>How can an <hi>indifferent</hi> man, ſeeking for <hi>Faith</hi> by <hi>your Rule,</hi> be ſatisfied <hi>they</hi> abuſe it more than <hi>you? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>By impartially conſidering the <hi>Rule,</hi> and comparing the <hi>Doctrines</hi> with it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis manifeſt you diſagree in the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of <hi>Scripture. R. p.</hi> 70.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Suppoſe we do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>What's the <hi>Way</hi> to arrive at the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of it? <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Humble</hi> and <hi>diligent attendance</hi> to it in the uſe of all <hi>good helps</hi> we can.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Certainly the <hi>interpreting</hi> it. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Interpreting</hi> is the <hi>ſearching</hi> for, and <hi>conjecturing</hi> at the <hi>ſonſe</hi> of it by thoſe helps.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Interpretation</hi> is <hi>Giving</hi> or <hi>Aſſigning</hi> to <hi>Words</hi> their <hi>ſenſe. R. p.</hi> 71.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Words had their <hi>ſignification</hi> given them in their firſt invention, and admit of alterations by <hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>cuſtom.</hi> No <hi>Interpreter</hi> gives the <hi>Words</hi> their <hi>ſenſe,</hi> but <hi>ſearcheth</hi> to find it out, and <hi>declareth</hi> what he finds.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Do not you accept that <hi>ſenſe</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> which your <hi>private Judgment</hi> conceives to be truly the <hi>meaning,</hi> and they in like manner, as they apprehend it ought to be <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>What they do, I know not. We having conſider'd well of all things which we know of to be conſider'd, muſt needs accept of the meaning which we judge to be true. And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whatever a man may be ſaid to <hi>accept,</hi> I think no
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:65387:36"/>man can <hi>believe</hi> what himſelf <hi>judgeth</hi> not to be <hi>true.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Is it not ſome clearer <hi>Light</hi> in you, muſt <hi>juſtifie</hi> you for <hi>judging</hi> them to be miſerable <hi>Abuſers</hi> of <hi>Scripture. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>We uſurp not to our ſelves a <hi>Pretorian</hi> power of <hi>judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> others, and therefore need nothing to <hi>juſtifie</hi> us for doing what we do not. That we ſay is this, that <hi>Hereticks,</hi> who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever are ſo, going about to ſupport their <hi>Errors</hi> by the <hi>Scripture,</hi> do abuſe it. All the <hi>Judgment</hi> we challenge touching <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> in <hi>particular,</hi> is no more but a <hi>Judgment</hi> of <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> to diſcern for <hi>our ſelves</hi> by the beſt means we can uſe, whoſe Doctrine is <hi>true,</hi> whoſe <hi>falſe,</hi> that we may know which to <hi>chuſe,</hi> and which to <hi>avoid.</hi> This we muſt do by the beſt <hi>Light</hi> that God hath given us, and by the <hi>ſame Light</hi> whereby we think our own Doctrine <hi>true,</hi> we muſt needs think theirs <hi>falſe;</hi> and as long as we do ſo, ſhun it. Which of us <hi>judgeth truly,</hi> we leave to the <hi>Judgment</hi> of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Your <hi>own Interpretation</hi> of it is, beyond all Evaſion, that which <hi>differences</hi> you from them, and ſo 'tis your <hi>peculiar</hi> or <hi>ſpecifick Rule</hi> of <hi>Faith. R. p.</hi> 72.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It <hi>differences</hi> us from <hi>them,</hi> but not our <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> from <hi>theirs,</hi> if theirs be <hi>Scripture:</hi> neither is it our <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> at all, but our <hi>Act</hi> about it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Do they who <hi>abuſe</hi> it, do it out of <hi>Wilfulneſs? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I prefume not to know.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Do they uſe their <hi>endeavoar</hi> to underſtand it? <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Neither know I that.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>fault</hi> conſiſts in pitching upon <hi>that</hi> for their <hi>Rule,</hi> which is indeed <hi>no Rule</hi> at all. <hi>R. p.</hi> 73.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>That follows not, a thouſand things may occaſion a <hi>miſinterpretation</hi> of the <hi>true Rule</hi> by ſome, thô neither you nor I can certainly ſay <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that</hi> was it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Your <hi>Rule</hi> miraculouſly makes <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Darkneſs</hi> conſiſtent, <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Belial</hi> very good friends. <hi>L p.</hi> 25.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>God give you <hi>repentance</hi> of this <hi>Blaſphemy. A. p.</hi> 28.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Your <hi>Rule</hi> equally <hi>patronizing true Faith</hi> and <hi>Hereſie,</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:65387:36"/>I had reaſon to affirm, that it <hi>inferred</hi> thoſe <hi>blaſphemous Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>If you will thus add <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> to <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> I cannot help it. Doth the <hi>Scripture</hi> indeed <hi>patronize Truth</hi> and <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> or <hi>can</hi> it do both? <hi>This alone</hi> you know is <hi>our Rule.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>This being my Charge, it was manifeſtly your Duty to ſhew it does not, and that <hi>only true Faith</hi> can be grounded on <hi>Scripture privately interpreted. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>You <hi>charge deſperately,</hi> and it concerns you to make good your <hi>charge,</hi> or to <hi>retreat</hi> betimes. <hi>Scripture</hi> is the <hi>Word of God,</hi> on which no <hi>Error</hi> can be <hi>grounded,</hi> howſoever it be <hi>interpreted.</hi> If men will make their <hi>own Interpretation</hi> the <hi>ground, Error</hi> enough may indeed be <hi>built</hi> on that, but none on <hi>Scripture. This</hi> is (as your ſelf) ſay, the <hi>Generical Rule</hi> we give. And <hi>this</hi> you ſay again is <hi>common</hi> to all <hi>Hereſies,</hi> that is, <hi>patroniteth true Faith and Hereſie, reconcileth Christ and Belial.</hi> I wiſh you may well <hi>diſcharge</hi> your ſelf of all this. It concerns you not a little.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>I only <hi>mention</hi> the <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> while I am <hi>charging you</hi> with it. <hi>R. p.</hi> 74.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>That <hi>ſhuffling</hi> will not ſerve your turn, when you are charged with <hi>blaſphemous words,</hi> firſt to <hi>acknowledge</hi> them to be <hi>blaſphemous,</hi> next to ſay, you were <hi>charging us</hi> with the <hi>blaſphemy,</hi> who never utter'd any thing like it, neither gave you the leaſt occaſion to utter it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Difference conſtituting</hi> your <hi>Proteſtant Rule,</hi> as diſtinguiſh'd from that of moſt abominable <hi>Hereticks,</hi> can only be <hi>[as my own Judgment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or others of my ſide, thus or thus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret the Letter of Scripture]</hi> and wriggle which way you will, there it will and muſt end at laſt. <hi>L. p.</hi> 26.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Who can expect loſs, but that where men pretend to <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility,</hi> they ſhould alſo pretend to <hi>know</hi> what is <hi>our Rule</hi> better than we our ſelves, poor <hi>fallible creatures</hi> do? <hi>A. p.</hi> 28.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>We take it as ill of you, that you will have us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>you</hi> before our own <hi>evident Reaſon. R. p.</hi> 74.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:65387:37"/>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I believe you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>You aſſure us <hi>plain Scripture</hi> is <hi>your Rule,</hi> that is, (as appears by your Diſcourſe) as you are <hi>ſuch</hi> a kind of <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>As I am a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> and a Member of the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plain,</hi> in what <hi>Points. R.p.</hi> 75.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>In <hi>all Points</hi> neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>To <hi>whom? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>To <hi>all</hi> that are <hi>capable</hi> of underſtanding plain words and ſenſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>By what kind of <hi>light? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>By the ſame whereby <hi>other Books</hi> are <hi>plain,</hi> as far as concerns the <hi>Literal ſenſe</hi> of the <hi>words</hi> and <hi>ſentences.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Experience tells us, That <hi>Scripture</hi> is not <hi>plain,</hi> even in the <hi>highest Points</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> ſince many follow it, and yet go aſtray. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>They go aſtray, not by <hi>following</hi> it, but by endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make it follow <hi>them.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>If it be ſo <hi>plain,</hi> all your <hi>uſeful helps</hi> are needleſs. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>How <hi>plain</hi> do you mean? Thô a <hi>Child's Leſſon</hi> be <hi>plain,</hi> yet needs he <hi>uſeful helps</hi> to learn it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scripture</hi> conceiv'd by you to be <hi>plain,</hi> can never be made out by you to be <hi>abſolutely certain. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It is enough for us to be <hi>morally certain</hi> of <hi>plain Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Socinians</hi> proceed upon <hi>Scripture, plain to them,</hi> as their <hi>Rule,</hi> and yet <hi>err. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis <hi>plain</hi> they <hi>err,</hi> by <hi>not adhering</hi> to <hi>plain Scripture,</hi> but to their own <hi>natural Reaſon,</hi> wherewith they uſe all their <hi>Art</hi> to make the <hi>Scripture</hi> agree, contrary to the moſt <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>obvious ſenſe</hi> of the <hi>words.</hi> The <hi>Interpretation</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> by any <hi>Sect</hi> of People, <hi>Romaniſts</hi> or <hi>others,</hi> is <hi>extrinſecal</hi> to the <hi>Rule,</hi> and no <hi>conſtitutive difference</hi> of it, as you imagine. <hi>A. p.</hi> 28.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Still <hi>Scripture as interpretable</hi> by <hi>your ſelves</hi> is your <hi>particular Rule,</hi> and not <hi>extrinſecal</hi> to it. <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:65387:37"/>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scripture</hi> as <hi>interpretable</hi> is not <hi>extrinſecal</hi> to our <hi>Rule,</hi> but is indeed our <hi>Rule;</hi> yet is the <hi>interpretation</hi> of it <hi>extrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> to it, which is that I ſaid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis your <hi>own Interpretation</hi> we ſaid was <hi>your Rule. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>We ſay 'tis not, and (according to you) it cannot be, who ſay that <hi>Scripture as interpretable</hi> is our <hi>Rule.</hi> I hope the <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation</hi> of a thing, and the <hi>thing interpretable</hi> are not one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Is not the <hi>Senſe</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> your <hi>Faith? R.</hi> 76.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>It is <hi>materially,</hi> that which we believe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Is not that <hi>eſſentially</hi> your <hi>particular Rule</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> that gives you your <hi>particular Faith? Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>What's all this Cloud of Words for? We have no <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Rule</hi> or <hi>Faith objectively</hi> taken, but that which was ordain'd of <hi>God</hi> for the <hi>common Rule</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>all Chriſtians.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Muſt I mind you again, that it is the very <hi>eſſence</hi> (as I may ſay) or nature of <hi>Interpretation</hi> to give you the ſenſe of the <hi>words</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> which in our caſe is your <hi>Faith. Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>You may ſay as you pleaſe, ſo you ſpeak to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. But that's not always your deſign, elſe would you ſpeak a little plainer. How often muſt I mind you, That the <hi>Scripture</hi> alone is our <hi>Rule,</hi> by underſtanding whereof we learn what to believe. The <hi>Interpretation</hi> of it (the <hi>eſſence</hi> whereof you talk of) is our <hi>ſearching</hi> for, and <hi>diſcovering</hi> of the <hi>ſenſe,</hi> and ſo our <hi>Learning</hi> to underſtand it, and not our <hi>Rule.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Venture boldly to declare what is your <hi>particular Rule.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>Our <hi>Rule</hi> in <hi>General</hi> is the <hi>Word of God;</hi> in <hi>particular</hi> (if you will needs have it ſo) and in <hi>contradiſtinction</hi> to <hi>your Rule</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Tradition,</hi> or <hi>Tradition only,</hi> 'tis the <hi>ſame Word written,</hi> or the <hi>Scripture</hi> only. And as differenced from both <hi>Romaniſts</hi> and other <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Sectaries,</hi> it is the ſame <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> ſtill, plainly delivering a <hi>ſenſe own'd</hi> and <hi>declared</hi> by the <hi>Primitive Church</hi> of Chriſt in the <hi>Three Creeds, Four first Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councils,</hi> and <hi>Harmony of the Fathers. A. p.</hi> 28.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:65387:38"/>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>Since <hi>Differences</hi> uſe to be <hi>Eſſential,</hi> whether are theſe words [<hi>own'd and declared,</hi> &amp;c.] at all <hi>eſſential</hi> or not? <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>To our <hi>Rule</hi> I ſuppoſe you mean. I ſay they are not: and ſo you have loſt a ſine Diſcourſe, <hi>p.</hi> 77, 78.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
               <p>If not, ſince, if you be <hi>orthodox,</hi> you ought to have a <hi>Rule eſſentially diſtinct</hi> from that of <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Sectaries,</hi> what is this <hi>Eſſential different Rule</hi> of your's. <hi>R. p.</hi> 76.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>I know no ſuch thing, as that the <hi>Orthodox</hi> and <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> ought to have <hi>ſeveral Rules eſſentially,</hi> as you ſay, <hi>diſtinct.</hi> Theſe may differ each from other in their <hi>Faith,</hi> and yet not in the <hi>Rule,</hi> thô in the <hi>interpreting</hi> of it they do.</p>
               <p>Thus have I endeavour'd (notwithſtanding the many <hi>Squibs</hi> you have thrown in the way to <hi>ſcare</hi> or <hi>vex</hi> me) to <hi>trace</hi> you ſtep by ſtep, where-ever I could diſcern the leaſt colour of <hi>Reaſon.</hi> And yet I confeſs is the far greater part of your long <hi>Letter</hi> unanſwer'd, and muſt be ſo for me. For ſhould I follow your frisking and playſome <hi>Fancy</hi> over hedges, and through puddles, as ſhe would lead me, I ſhould too well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Character of <hi>an everlaſting Trifler,</hi> for <hi>running after Butterflies,</hi> which you have ſo friendly beſtow'd on,</p>
            </sp>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
